<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="text-1"><pb facs="#f000"/>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="inline">
                  <placeName>Woodbridge</placeName> 
                  <date when="1826-04-05">4/5th
                  1826</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
               <salute>Esteemed Friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               Not having heard anything<lb/>
               more respecting the intended Publication I am not<lb/>
               aware whether the design has been abandon'd, or<lb/>
               whether its accomplishment may be so far advanced<lb/>
               as to render the annex'd too late for insertion.<lb/>
               If in time, and worth using, they are heartily<lb/>
               at thy Service. I only wish I could have sent<lb/>
               thee somewhat worthier of thy acceptance, but if<lb/>
               these serve to show that I wish well to<lb/>
               thy efforts, &amp; the object they have in view<lb/>
               one end is answered.
            </p>
            <p>
               In the first of the<lb/>
               annexed trifles I have endeavor'd briefly<lb/>
               to express some of those better feelings which<lb/>
               I cannot but think the common dictates of Nature must<lb/>
               excite in the unfortunate Slave Mother, in reference to<lb/>
               her equally miserable Child. But as I believe instances<lb/>
               occur, would they were more frequent, in which through<lb/>
               the labours of Missionaries &amp;c the Consolations of the Gospel<lb/>
               are opened to those injured &amp; devoted Beings, I have en-<lb/>
               deavour'd in the second short article to embody some of<lb/>
               the thoughts &amp; feelings of a Converted Negro –– still, I hope, without<lb/>
               compromise of the principle. Surely the sentiment contained<lb/>
               in the concluding Verse must occur to such an one –– for in<lb/>
               my view deplorable as is the Bondage of the unhappy Negro<lb/>
               the Slavery of the Enslaver, the hopeless yoke of which<lb/>
               he is the bigoted Victim, implies a thraldom yet not more<lb/> dreadful ––
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Thine respectfully</salute><lb/>
               <signed><abbr>B. B.</abbr></signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         </body></text>