<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Death of the Slave</title>
            <author>James Edmeston</author>
            <editor>Mary Anne Rawson</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Mary Anne Rawson's The Bow in the Cloud (1834): A Digital Edition and Network Analysis</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Published in the Bow in the Cloud (1834), pp. 71–73.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         
         <div type="poem">
         <head type="headnote">The Funeral of the African in his native land is accompanied by wailing, and by all the deep-marked emotions of savage grief; but, in a state of Slavery, death is welcomed as a most Joyous event, and the funeral is accompanied by the most extreme exultation; for they believe that they shall then return to their home and their friends, the scenes of their infancy, and to all they love.</head>
         
            <lg type="quatrain" n="1"><l><hi rend="smallcaps">Rejoice</hi> for the dead, with the shout and the song!</l>
         <l>He has borne all his pain, he has suffered his wrong,</l>
         <l>He has burst from his chain, and his labour is o'er,</l>
         <l>He will start at the lash of the driver no more!</l></lg>
         
            <lg type="quatrain" n="2"><l>Full many a heavy slow year has passed by,</l>
         <l>Since they tore him away from his palm-hut to die;</l>
         <l>But now he has gone where his suffering ends,</l>
         <l>And merry to-night will he be with his friends!</l></lg>
         
            <lg type="quatrain" n="3"><l>How his wife will rejoice, in whose bosom he lay!</l> 
         <l>And his children, who ran round him every day!</l>
         <l>The baby Quenana, who sat on his knee,</l>
         <l>What a tall and a sweet, blooming girl she will be!</l></lg>
         
         <lg type="quatrain"><l>You remember the night when the moon was sofair,</l>
         <l>And we gathered around for our summer sport there;</l>
         <l>When the war-cry was raised, we were filled with dismay,</l>
         <l>And the robbers of men bore us off for their prey.</l></lg>
         
            <lg type="quatrain"><l>O Guinea! the thought of thy forests how dear!</l>
         <l>Thy toucan and tinamon often we hear;</l>
         <l>Well!--a little more labour, and we too shall be</l>
         <l>In the dance with our friends round the wide-spreading tree!</l></lg>
         
         <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James Edmeston</hi>.</signed>
         
         <dateline><placeName><hi rend="italic">Homerton</hi></placeName>, <date when="1826">1826</date>.</dateline></div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
