<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Funeral Oration</title>
            <author>John Ely</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head><hi rend="small-caps">Supposed to be delivered at the grave of Wm. Wilberforce, Esq.</hi></head>
            
            <p><hi rend="small-caps">Many</hi> an imposing spectacle has, in the course of ages, been exhibited within these venerable walls; but never did they present one more instructive than that of this day. When monarchs have received the royal unction, thousands have crowded together in gratulation; and whilst the ceremonial has been graced by the flower of British chivalry and British beauty, a nation’s loyalty has responded from the millions of British subjects. The wail of many a requiem has sounded solemnly and touchingly among these aisles and these arches, when the victor or the statesman has been laid in his “bed of glory,” honoured by the tears of prince and people; — or when some royal scion which British fondness cherished, and on which British hopes were suspended, has been rent away from a stock left branchless and barren, and a nation’s passionate grief has all but equalled the cry of Egypt’s night of calamity. — But who are these that gather around that coffin? and who is he whom they attend in solemn procession to the sepulchre? No herald proclaims the style of the dead; no coronet glitters in mockery upon the pall; no banners, rent in battle, and wrested from the vanquished foe, wave over the bier; no passion of grief betokens the demise of some cherished fondling of the people, and no blank stupefaction indicates one of those unlooked-for catastrophes which sometimes smite a whole nation’s darling hope. No — princes, statesmen, legislators have mingled in the funeral train with Britain’s selectest citizens, that they may pay the last tribute to one whose virtues and philanthropy were his chief distinctions; that tribute, more honourable to themselves than to him, they pay to <hi rend="small-caps">the Friend of Humanity and the Liberator of Africa</hi>.</p>
            
            <p>It belongs to biography to narrate where Wilberforce was born, and what was the course of his personal history; the offices of this day are due to the eloquence, the energy, the perseverance, and the piety which characterized the negro’s advocate, and wrought the negro’s liberation. He had already pondered the wrongs of the African race, when, in the year 1787, a stranger presented himself before him, and moved him to become their champion. That stranger had himself foregone literary honours and ecclesiastical preferment, under the strong pressure of a necessity laid upon him by conscientious solicitude to annihilate the horrors of the slave trade; he had dedicated his life to this great object, — and, in prosecution of it, he travelled thousands of miles, year by year, — suffered unmeasured fatigue and obloquy, — moved town after town and province after province, — and expended every corporeal and mental power upon his voluntary and exhausting undertaking. Though himself but an isolated individual; though the system of enormity to which he opposed himself was supported by the power of the civilized world, while it desolated a whole continent of savages; and though the British slave trade was supposed to be to Britain the nursery of her sailors, the prop of her colonies, and the source of her wealth, — yet he resolved on nothing less than the annihilation of the criminal and horrible traffic; and he never rested till he saw the accomplishment of his aim. But for Thomas Clarkson, even Wilberforce had not been impelled to the great work which has secured for him this day’s honourable tribute.</p>
            
            <p>The impulse was foreign, but it acted on a mind prepared to sympathize in the benevolent design. Wilberforce listened to the appalling representations which were made to him, he carefully investigated the authorities on which they rested, and at length he committed himself to all the responsibilities of the negro’s advocacy in the British senate. His eye fixed on the scene of negro oppression, and his heart revolved the enormity of negro wrong, till his spirit melted with pity and burned with indignation. He saw the ships of this nefarious traffic hovering like so many birds of prey upon the Gold Coast, — while from the shore to the very interior of the continent, tribe was exasperated against tribe, that the captive of savage war might be brought a slave to the fomentors of that barbarous strife; — while justice was abused in the arraignment and condemnation of miserable victims for crimes which they had never committed, that they might be sold for British gold; and while kidnappers, ascending the rivers, and concealing themselves amid the bushes, assailed at nightfall the unsuspecting inhabitants in their villages, and firing their dwellings, conveyed their persons to the shore to be shipped across the seas and sold into interminable slavery. Then he turned to contemplate the horrors of the middle passage: he saw the wretched captives bound with shackles one to another; crowded into the hold without the power of standing upright, or even lying at their length; breathing a noisome, suffocating atmosphere; and for exercise brought upon deck, and there compelled to dance by the terror of the lash. Particular cases of cruelty were pictured before him, and among the rest that of the mere babe scourged because it would not — could not eat; its limbs, swollen with the scourge, thrust into water heated so as to scald and excoriate the flesh; the poor infant then tied to a log, and after two or three days scourged again till it expired; when its wretched mother was, by a refinement of brutality, called upon deck, to drop, with averted eyes, its poor lacerated body into the sea. He saw the despairing victims of oppression plunge themselves into the ocean, waving their exulting hands as they escaped from their ruthless oppressors and sunk to rise no more; while still larger numbers perished by disease, and of eighty thousand Africans annually shipped upon the shore, one-eighth portion expired in the passage. Then he turned his eyes to the isles of the western world, and saw the markets where the negro was valued and bought and sold, and witnessed his seasoning to new and laborious occupations, and heard the groan and estimated the degradation of men reduced to perpetual slavery.</p>
            
            <p>The God of providence fits the instruments which he raises up, for the exigencies by which their agency is demanded. From the contemplation of visions like these, a morbid sensibility, though it might offer the tribute of a few tears, would shortly have recoiled; and a heart hardened by the collision of worldly strife would speedily have forgotten the exciting theme. Impotence would have shrunk from the task of interference; indolence would speedily have relaxed exertion; enthusiasm would have consumed itself, after a few disappointments and unavailing efforts. Good intention and persevering zeal would have been ineffective, if unsustained by well-balanced powers of intellect. Eloquence, a manly and persuasive eloquence, was moreover indispensable, that the advocate might depict the scenes of oppression, and argue the questions of justice and policy, and kindle the enthusiasm of the senate and the nation. The champion of such a cause must also himself be of unimpeachable excellence; and none but one possessing the highest style of christian character could have commanded the attention of statesmen, or have endured the keen-eyed vigilance of interested and malignant hostility. Wilberforce possessed the natural and moral attributes required in the discharge of his high and voluntary service. For twenty years he prosecuted his work of christian charity. His clear and comprehensive knowledge of the case, his argumentative and impassioned eloquence, his patience in the details of inquiry, his temper in the hour of provocation, his unwearied perseverance amid difficulty and disappointment, his holy zeal for humanity and justice, — won for him respectful attention, and secured ultimate success, while they have given to his name a glory as pure as it is brilliant, in the admiration of which partizanship forgets its strifes, and a nation testifies its homage: none but baseness, as unblushing as it is degraded, utters the dissonance of reproach; and the only reproach which even that baseness attempts is a virtual tribute to the philanthropy which it scorns and belies.</p>
            
            <p>This is not the occasion on which to give the details of a conflict which was sustained with equal wisdom and magnanimity through so long a succession of years, and which issued in a triumph as complete as it was glorious. In the progress of that conflict, with what calm dignity did he, who now sleeps in that coffin, meet ridicule and reproach, — with what perspicacity did he trace the involutions, and with what energy did he unravel the knots of sophistry, — with what eloquence did he rouse the spirit of the lukewarm to fervour and activity! He met the interested with evidence proving that policy was on the side of justice, whilst he indignantly denounced wrong, as that which no policy could justify; his graphic descriptions and pathetic appeals wakened the indifferent to zeal; he secured on his side the virtue and talent of the senate. It is a splendid eulogy of his moral greatness, to say that Burke, and Fox, and Pitt, and Canning were contented to be his coadjutors in his great enterprise; and that they to whom all others conceded pre-eminence, conceded to him pre-eminence in the sacred cause which he had espoused. They who differed with him on questions of political expediency, yet honoured him for his philanthropy and piety, and bowed with him at the foot of the cross. They who, at different times, were his political adversaries, were also at different times his political allies, and did homage to his moral greatness when they were most alienated from his political opinions. The christian, the philanthropist, and the legislator, found in him an advocate and an example. His humanity was but an emanation from his piety; he loved and laboured for mankind because he loved his God. No foul spot of dishonour rested on his christian character, no taint of selfishness or hypocrisy gave just occasion for the malevolent to sneer at the principles by which he professed to be actuated. His piety was as uniform as it was fervent; and his zeal as untiring as it was holy. He forgot himself, and sought only the glory of his Lord and the happiness of mankind; and the mercy of heaven has granted to him the singular happiness of witnessing the consummation of his great enterprise.</p>
            
            <p>Long will the recollection of this day’s scene — long will the name and memory of Wilberforce, live in the hearts of the good; and when future ages shall ask for what his statue is erected here, the silent majesty of the marble shall reply — not to perpetuate the remembrance of victory in war, — not to signalize the possession of supreme power, — but to record the services rendered to humanity by a christian philanthropist, and to awaken in the heart of every spectator the love of God and man.</p>
            <byline><persName ref="../personography.xml#ely_j">John Ely</persName>.
            <placeName>Leeds</placeName>.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
