<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>West-Indian Slavery</title>
        <author>William Howitt</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Publication Information</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="poem">
        <lg>
          <l>&quot;Slaves cannot breathe in England.&quot; That is true,</l>
          <l>But they who forge the chains of Slavery do.</l>
          <l>The British senator, at midnight raves</l>
          <l>Of liberty-and holds bis hundred slaves.</l>
          <l>The British merchant, whose adventurous soul</l>
          <l>Dares for his gain the terrors of each pole;</l>
          <l>The British gentleman, in freedom's isle;</l>
          <l>The British father, basking in the smile</l>
          <l>Of love and laughing childhood,––nay, even he</l>
          <l>Who boasts, &quot;the blood of Christ hath made him free;&quot;</l>
          <l>All, sorely tainted with the gainful lust,</l>
          <l>Deem Slavery wise; nay, every thing but––just.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>True,––the foul scene that brands us and defiles,</l>
          <l>Is held at distance in our Indian isles.</l>
          <l>True,––no blood trickles from our bondsman's sores;</l>
          <l>No fetters clank, no lash sounds on our shores.</l>
          <l>Oh! that they were but near us! Then the soul</l>
          <l>Of an indignant people would controul</l>
          <l>Slavery's fell spirit, with that mighty word</l>
          <l>Which tyrants ever trembled as they heard,</l>
          <l>Vain would the subtlest sophistry be then,</l>
          <l>Or the feigned terrors of insatiate men.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Ah! they who deem themselves so proudly laid</l>
          <l>In freedom's lap that none can make afraid,</l>
          <l>Would never, never see the pleading face</l>
          <l>Of woman bowed in pitiless disgrace;</l>
          <l>In sins and sorrows which perforce transmute</l>
          <l>Immortal man into a reasoning brute.</l>
          <l>Ah! they to whom the sweet and hallowed scope</l>
          <l>Of life's strong sympathies, and death's strong hope,</l>
          <l>Than life itself are dearer, holier far,</l>
          <l>Would never see them trampled as they are!</l>
          <l>The husband, leaning on the breast which nursed</l>
          <l>His happy children, never would see cursed</l>
          <l>The groaning negro; doomed to hear the wail</l>
          <l>Of child and mother severed at the sale,</l>
          <l>To meet no more,––but sent, like him, to share</l>
          <l>All the vile crimes and miseries of despair.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>But these-are distant;––we behold them not;</l>
          <l>And we live sweetly in our pleasant lot,</l>
          <l>To talk of England's virtues––England's fame­</l>
          <l>And charities that will embalm her name.</l>
          <l>O happy generous country of the free,</l>
          <l>With not a slave––but what's beyond the sea!</l>
          <l>'Twixt thee and infamy an ocean rolls;</l>
          <l>But, will it wash the stains of cruel souls?</l>
          <l>When the sun looks upon those glowing isles</l>
          <l>Where every thing, but thy sad victims, smiles,</l>
          <l>Thou dost not see them––but are they not seen</l>
          <l>In the heart's sun-light far more bright and keen?</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Sleep on, thou glorious island, midst thy waves;</l>
          <l>Sweet be thy slumbers,––in thee are no slaves!</l>
          <l>Sleep on, thou queen of ocean!––not a groan</l>
          <l>Of the spent negro shall approach thy throne.</l>
          <l>The whip, the chain, fierce torture, hopeless toil,</l>
          <l>Far be they banished to some savage soil.</l>
          <l>In thee are tender hearts, and minds that make</l>
          <l>Thee loved and honoured for thy mercies' sake.</l>
          <l>Lo! how thy swarming children duly flock</l>
          <l>To His high temple, whom they dare not mock.</l>
          <l>Hark! to the contrite sinner's pleading tone,</l>
          <l>&quot;Oh, Father, take from me this heart of stone!&quot;</l>
          <l>Thy children worship, almost from their birth,</l>
          <l>The God who made of one blood all the earth;­––</l>
          <l>The God of love, who sent His Son to give</l>
          <l>The law of mutual love to all who live.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Sleep on, fair island, midst such plenteous streams</l>
          <l>Of righteousness––what should disturb thy dreams?</l>
          <l>Horrors and crimes, so distant, can't defile</l>
          <l>Thy emerald breast––thou art a saintly isle!</l>
          <l>Aye, sleep! but know that Freedom not the more</l>
          <l>Will fold her pinions till thy trance is o'er.</l>
          <l>Her wings have swept the western world,––her shrill</l>
          <l>Trumpet alarms, what earthly power may still?</l>
          <l>Those mighty realms, from Erie's northern lake,</l>
          <l>Even to the far Magellan are awake.</l>
          <l>The night is past,––there mind has reached its birth;</l>
          <l>Men cast with scorn their fetters to the earth.</l>
          <l>From Hayti's neighbouring state, what kindred cries</l>
          <l>Call to thy captives,––&quot;Ho! Arise! Arise!&quot;</l>
          <l>They will arise! At thine, or at their call,</l>
          <l>Mercy will melt, or vengeance burst their thrall.</l>
          <l>And then must fly thy spirit-frozen dream</l>
          <l>At a world's plaudits, or at scorn's extreme.</l>
          <l>The saviour-isle!––the loved!––almost adored!­</l>
          <l>For crimes atoned,––and human rights restored.</l>
          <l>Or agonized spectatress of the chain</l>
          <l>Shivered by hands long stretched to thee in vain;</l>
          <l>The victory won––firm planted Freedom's tree!</l>
          <l>And the world blest,––but, shame bequeathed to thee.</l>
        </lg>
        <signed>
          <persName ref="../personography.xml#howitt_w">William Howitt</persName>
        </signed>
        <dateline>
          <placeName>Nottingham</placeName>, <date when="1826">1826</date>.
        </dateline>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
