<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lot of the Slave</title>
            <author>R. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>The Bow in the Cloud: A Digital Scholarly Edition</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Published in the Bow in the Cloud (1834), pp. 225–31</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
      <text>
         <body>
            <div type="poem" n="1">
               <lg>
                  <head>[The following, though not, strictly speaking, "a true story," is founded on statements not to be disproved; and narratives well authenticated would furnish many other particulars, of at least as dark a character.]</head>
                  <l>Loved, as a mother loves the babe she bore,</l>
                  <l>Watches, toils, sighs, and loves it but the more,</l>
                  <l>An infant negro, in the Westem isles,</l>
                  <l>Springs into life; -- the captive-mother smiles:</l>
                  <l>For love will smile, however brief the joy;</l>
                  <l>And her's is brief: -- O might she tend her boy!</l>
                  <l>From nature's fountain due supplies to yield</l>
                  <l>Might she but pause and quit the weary field!</l>
                  <l>No: -- ere his birth, -- when fast her hour drew on,</l>
                  <l>Burdened and faint, her task must yet be done,</l>
                  <l>Short respite, short repose that frame must feel;</l>
                  <l>Can she not stand to labour? -- she must kneel.</l>
                  <l>Some interval at length even avarice gave,</l>
                  <l>In pity? -- nay; his property to save;</l>
                  <l>But that is past, and she again must bear</l>
                  <l>The sun, the lash, and to a stranger's care,</l>
                  <l>(An aged negress for the field unfit,)</l>
                  <l>Till day decline, her nurseling must commit;</l>
                  <l>Nor dare a mother's fondness to express,</l>
                  <l>Till nature droop, heart-sick with weariness.</l>
                  <l>Yet even thus, some comfort she derives</l>
                  <l>From every sight of him; he grows, he thrives,</l>
                  <l>Her hourly solace. Who -- what fiend could bear</l>
                  <l>From her fond arm that one delight to tear?</l>
                  <l>Ah! 'tis her owner's property, not her's,</l>
                  <l>And avarice with soft pity ne'er confers.</l>
                  <l>In want of gold, he sees a fit resource</l>
                  <l>In that young slave, and with no more remorse,</l>
                  <l>Or even less, than he who sells his horse,</l>
                  <l>He names a sum, -- 'tis paid, -- the deed is done, --</l>
                  <l>Tears, prayers, avail her not, -- the child is gone.</l>
                  <l>Frantic she shrieks, she howls in agony</l>
                  <l>Around her master's dwelling. That shrill cry,</l>
                  <l>Can he not silence it? -- it breaks his sleep;</l>
                  <l>Is there no remedy? -- there is; -- the whip!</l>
                  <l>This is the anodyne he deems the best,</l>
                  <l>To soothe her spirit? -- no, -- to bring him rest.</l>
                  <l>And from that hour, perchance, his court she trod</l>
                  <l>In stillness, -- but "her cry went up to God."</l>
                  <l>He, the poor infant-victim, wept not long;</l>
                  <l>Self-interest bade them shew a thing so young</l>
                  <l>Such tenderness as even the young of brutes</l>
                  <l>Miss not, -- that care the owner's purpose suits;</l>
                  <l>Though times there are, when cruelty's fell reign</l>
                  <l>Hears even the voice of interest plead in vain;</l>
                  <l>When gain, so fondly sought, less joy imparts,</l>
                  <l>Than torturing human limbs and human hearts.</l>
                  <l>His lot was milder, if it be more mild</l>
                  <l>To spare a slave than slay him when a child:</l>
                  <l>His childhood past, he grew a hardy boy,</l>
                  <l>And entered early on a slave's employ;</l>
                  <l>Early and long inured to daily pain,</l>
                  <l>To dress the stubborn soil, and plant the cane;</l>
                  <l>Dull, heartless, hopeless toil, that nought repays</l>
                  <l>For all the waste of life's first, fairest days.</l>
                  <l>Smiling in beauty all the land may be,</l>
                  <l>But can an eye enslaved that beauty see,</l>
                  <l>Or seeing, taste? -- it smiles but on the free.</l>
                  <l>Toiled he in hope, the thought of future gain</l>
                  <l>Might nerve his soul long sorrow to sustain;</l>
                  <l>Saw he in distant prospect, freedom's light,</l>
                  <l>That beam, though faint, might cheer his aching sight;</l>
                  <l>But should his hands, when resting from the field,</l>
                  <l>Be active yet, and should the effort yield</l>
                  <l>Some humble fruit -- precarious rights are his!</l>
                  <l>His little all a lawless white may seize,</l>
                  <l>And if he dared defend it, with his life</l>
                  <l>He pays the forfeit of that blameless strife.</l>
                  <l>Or were he freed, unless the proof appear</l>
                  <l>In every point indisputably clear,</l>
                  <l>Though guiltless of a fault, his doom may be</l>
                  <l>A fresh, remediless captivity.</l>
                  <l>But trained from childhood, William suffered not,</l>
                  <l>In all their weight, the hardships of his lot;</l>
                  <l>Stung by no memory of a happier day, --</l>
                  <l>A Paradise for ever passed away, --</l>
                  <l>Healthy and strong, his task accomplished well,</l>
                  <l>On him the whip's dread vengeance rarely fell;</l>
                  <l>Though through the gang oft sounds its fierce assault</l>
                  <l>On all who loiter, -- feebleness their fault;</l>
                  <l>And he not quite escaped, but his dark day</l>
                  <l>Of misery had not dawned, -- 'twas on its way.</l>
                  <l>It chanced among the females, one there was</l>
                  <l>Whom William loved, for Nature's bounteous laws</l>
                  <l>Even Slavery cannot wholly set aside;</l>
                  <l>Their love was mutual; she became his bride,</l>
                  <l>And in each other they were happy; true,</l>
                  <l>The bonds were slightly knit that joined the two;</l>
                  <l>The marriage covenant, if the owner please,</l>
                  <l>Whatever rites have sealed it, vanishes.</l>
                  <l>But they were faithful, and 'twas their's to prove</l>
                  <l>The sweetness first, and then the grief of love.</l>
                  <l>Fanny, for William's sake, performed with zeal</l>
                  <l>The allotted task, afraid lest he should feel</l>
                  <l>The pang of sympathy, more keen, more deep</l>
                  <l>Than even his own beneath the ruthless whip.</l>
                  <l>And love, long time, sustained her, but at length</l>
                  <l>Failed to supply the want of firmer strength.</l>
                  <l>Just then, when first her energy declined,</l>
                  <l>Their manager -- a wretch of foulest mind, --</l>
                  <l>Had eyed her wantonly, and strove to gain</l>
                  <l>Her favour, but enraged to sue in vain,</l>
                  <l>Vowed inly dire revenge; his victim soon</l>
                  <l>Proved all its fury; on one sultry noon</l>
                  <l>Faintly she cast the hoe, the driver's scourge</l>
                  <l>Fell heavily her lingering hand to urge.</l>
                  <l>She strove, but failed again, -- a fiercer stroke</l>
                  <l>Crimsoned the lash, -- poor William saw and spoke:</l>
                  <l>His words were hasty, and were soon conveyed</l>
                  <l>To the stern manager. "Bring both!" he said.</l>
                  <l>They stand before him; for the other, each</l>
                  <l>Pleads strongly, though in short and broken speech.</l>
                  <l>Vain cry! can he compassionate their smart?</l>
                  <l>He feel the groan that bursts a Negro's heart?</l>
                  <l>His malice smiles to see the whip fulfil</l>
                  <l>Its fiery office and his barbarous will;</l>
                  <l>And yet unsatisfied, his deadly hate</l>
                  <l>Resolves the faithful pair to separate.</l>
                  <l>But Fanny from that hour no more revived;</l>
                  <l>She sickened, drooped, and perished. -- William lived, --</l>
                  <l>But, O, how changed! how spiritless! -- his eye</l>
                  <l>Was cold and dim; his step moved heavily;</l>
                  <l>Needless before, the stimulating scourge</l>
                  <l>Now scarce avails his tardiness to urge.</l>
                  <l>Slow steals his life in wretchedness away,</l>
                  <l>Till dawns the long-desired, the closing day.</l>
                  <l>There is a balm that o'er the bruised heart</l>
                  <l>Whose anguish mocks the power of healing art,</l>
                  <l>Sheds ease, hope, gladness, heaven: -- there is a name</l>
                  <l>Thrills through the penitent's dissolving frame,</l>
                  <l>Foretelling endless rest, the gift of Him --</l>
                  <l>The Son of Man, -- the Son of God, the stream</l>
                  <l>Of whose rich blood the troubled soul can clear</l>
                  <l>From its foul burden, guilt, and shame, and fear.</l>
                  <l>Feels he that balm, transforming all his lot?</l>
                  <l>Knows he that name? -- Alas! he knows it not.</l>
                  <l>Heralds of peace had visited that isle,</l>
                  <l>Charged with the news that makes even Slavery smile,</l>
                  <l>But the white rulers held the theme unmeet</l>
                  <l>For Negro-minds, -- too, too divinely sweet!</l>
                  <l>Some had indeed been taught, but not a word</l>
                  <l>Of that inspiring news had William heard,</l>
                  <l>His Christian owner seeing little need</l>
                  <l>To teach the animal so high a creed.</l>
                  <l>Hopeless and blind, he died, and One whose eye</l>
                  <l>No thought escapes, has judged him -- righteously.</l>
                  <l>And this is Slavery! and they are men</l>
                  <l>That forge, and fix, and rivet fast the chain,</l>
                  <l>And o'er their brethren hold a tyrant's sway!</l>
                  <l>Not all a tyrant's spirit will display;</l>
                  <l>Not all will play the demon, but all may.</l>
                  <l>And that dread power, in hands however just,</l>
                  <l>Is an unwarranted, tremendous trust.</l>
                  <l>Shall a supremacy to man be given</l>
                  <l>Unquestioned, absolute, like that of Heaven?</l>
                  <l>Slavery! of all enormities the worst</l>
                  <l>Man's fall has gendered, or his madness nurst!</l>
                  <l>Earth teems with crime, and one, above the rest,</l>
                  <l>Against high Heaven uplifts its daring crest;</l>
                  <l>But War, even War, in guilt, in infamy,</l>
                  <l>In hardihood and horror, -- yields to thee!</l>
                  <l>Shame on thy bold pretence, endured so long,</l>
                  <l>Thy right to perpetrate a matchless wrong!</l>
                  <l>Drop thy proud plume, bend low thy hated brow,</l>
                  <l>The eyes of Britons scan the features now.</l>
                  <l>Thy long, dark reign is ending, -- die to be</l>
                  <l>The scorn and wonder of futurity.</l>
                  <l>Time shall be when thy annals shall appear</l>
                  <l>Unnatural fictions to the sickening ear,</l>
                  <l>Though history's faithful page can ne'er recount</l>
                  <l>Of half thy loathsome crimes the sad amount.</l>
                  <l>Perish! and may kind Heaven a world forgive</l>
                  <l>That suffered thee so many an age to live.</l>
                  <l>C.</l>
                  <l>N---.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </body>
      </text>
   </TEI>
   