<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Luke X.25–37</title>
            <author>Maria Stevens</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Mary Anne Rawson's The Bow in the Cloud (1834): A Digital Scholarly Edition</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Published in the Bow in the Cloud, pp. 3.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>
            <lb/><span style="small-caps">How</span> often have we paused with admiring delight on the forcible words by which our Lord replied to him who asked of Him, "And who is my neighbour?" The answer was couched in a parable calculated to arrest attention; the closing application to the conscience of the hearer being equally calculated to enforce conviction. We admit the excellency of this exposition of brotherly-kindness; happy are we if at the same time we receive the admonition, "Go <hi rend="italic">thou</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">do</hi> likewise." The human heart is not, however, quick to respond to the voice of human misery. What costs us little we can readily bestow; and words and sighs and wishes sometimes are heard with an imposing semblance of sympathy, which persuades even our own heart that we feel another's woe. <hi rend="italic">Practical</hi> sympathy is little known -- its gracious and spiritual character still less. We condemn the priest mentioned in the parable, who, averting his eyes from the spectacle of misery that lay in his way, passed by on the other side; we lament the indifference or indolence of him who, drawing nearer, looked upon the object before him, yet passed on without attempting to succour him in his distress; yet, it is to be apprehended, that in many instances persons thus free to censure transgression in others are found guilty of the same offence. Are we occupied so fully in our own pursuits as to remain destitute of reflection upon the claims of our fellow-men? Are we disdainful or negligent of the miseries which we have looked upon, silencing our own consciences by pretending we can do little to relieve? We are in this case verily guilty before God and know not the law which enjoins that we "love our neighbour as ourselves." What a contrast is seen in the spirit and course of the few who, like the Samaritan, have hearts to sympathize, eyes to behold, and hands to administer to the needy! These tread the way of love; possessing the principle of brotherhood in its practical fruits; and, amidst these, some there are, who, possessing it, put forth its sacred energies in a sanctified expression, comprehending in their charity the interests of eternity with those of time. Wounds inflicted by the enemies of the soul are seen and commiserated; the healing virtue of that salvation which alone can staunch the wounds, or bind up the broken heart, is earnestly applied: and, not satisfied with a temporary endeavour, provision is made, by every exertion that can be given, for the placing of the soul within the dwelling-places where God may be more fully known. Many zealous and believing souls have evinced this charity; and the bleeding, dying, stripped, and destitute in spirit, have been housed and fed and healed, to the glory of redeeming love. So <hi rend="italic">God's</hi> charity has dealt to us, inhabitants of a guilty world; he has looked upon our deadly wound -- he has descended to the work of mercy -- he has undertaken our cure, and provided the oil and the wine whereby the sorrows and sins of men may be dried up. He has opened the courts of his house; the banqueting-house also, where, by perpetual ministrations of grace, he carries on our cure. All this is ours, as believers, and puts on us a sacred obligation <hi rend="italic">freely to give</hi> what we have <hi rend="italic">freely received</hi>. In <hi rend="italic">our measure</hi> let us "go, and do likewise;" -- as having the mind of Christ, evince it, in works of Christian love. Let us commiserate the suffering bodies of men, much more their wounded souls. And to whom may we more properly turn the direction of these designs than to the unhappy Negro, our brother, our neighbour by blood; who truly has fallen among thieves, who have stripped him naked, and wounded him; and to whose case we might well apply the words, "and left him half dead?" Great have been the exertions, on which the Divine blessing has descended, through which mercy dawns on Afric's sons; but liberation from the human yoke is not enough; Christians cannot be satisfied to rest in the breaking of the captive's chain which binds him to oppressing men; -- there is a higher interest, a dearer freedom, an abiding and eternal liberty, of which we must desire our brethren may partake. Let then the sigh heard for the sorrows of the slave be one of practical and <hi rend="italic">Christian</hi> sympathy: while seeking the redress of his wrongs as a fellow-creature, let the liberation of his soul, from the judgment he will otherwise inherit as a fellow-sinner, be the steady, the believing object kept in view. And may the Eternal Spirit open the way for bringing home many of these by the instrumentality of those who shall bring them, take care of them, and provide for them a Christian refuge -- <hi rend="italic">a consecrated inn!</hi> When the journey of life is done, we shall rejoice in the Lord's acceptance of such works of the Spirit; and, although the work is free, and hopes not for a reward on its own merit (for of this we can have none), we may believe that the words of our Lord will be verified, who said, "These cannot recompense thee, but thou shalt be recompensed at the resurrection of the just."
            <lb/>
            <lb/><span style="small-caps">Maria Stevens</span>.
            <lb/>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Knaresborough</hi>.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

