<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>LIBERTAS: QUAE SERA TAMEN, RESPEXIT, &amp;c. &amp;c.</title>
            <author>John Parker</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Mary Anne Rawson's The Bow in the Cloud (1834): A Digital Scholarly Edition</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Published in the Bow in the Cloud, pp. 278–81.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lg>
            <l><hi rend="smallcaps">'Tis</hi> o'er. -- Britannia rules without a stain;</l>
            <l>The Queen of Nations is herself again;</l>
            <l>O'er the vast climes that call her monarch -- lord --</l>
            <l>Where'er her arts or sceptre has explored, --</l>
            <l>From the gay coasts whence comes the rising sun,</l>
            <l>To those he sinks in when his race is run, --</l>
            <l>Search as you will her realms from sea to sea,</l>
            <l>You'll find her still the "Freest of the Free."</l>
         </lg>
            <lg><l>Star of my country! what can Fame entwine</l>
            <l>For Rome or Athens, that will vie with thine?</l>
            <l>Of Spartan liberty though Poets feign,</l>
            <l>The Helot groaned beneath a Spartan chain;</l>
            <l>With "equal laws" Colombia may resound,</l>
            <l>Those "equal laws" the Negro has not found;</l>
            <l>In arts of war, the Franks our rivals move,</l>
            <l>But are they rivals in the arts of love?</l>
            <l>Star of my country! what so bright a course</l>
            <l>As thine, of freedom both th' effect and source?</l>
            <l>How just, let those declare who know it best;</l>
            <l>How godlike, say, ye Children of the West!</l>
            <l>Chartered thyself, thou hadst the power to save,</l>
            <l>And in its volume you include the Slave.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>Why then those tears do Nubian mothers pour?</l>
            <l>Why echoes Albion their grief with more?</l>
            <l>Why, when this solid globe from pole to pole</l>
            <l>Rings with loud anthems, recent from the soul,</l>
            <l>Falls there, as joyous trains and pomps pass by,</l>
            <l>A sympathetic drop from every eye?</l>
            <l>Struck with a sight so strange, I turn and pause,</l>
            <l>But 'tis in England that I see the cause.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>For at that hour when all the welkin rung</l>
            <l>With plaudits, saints or angels might have sung,</l>
            <l>On his last bed, himself o'erjoyed as they,</l>
            <l>The Negro's Friend -- the "Liberator" lay:</l>
            <l>It seemed as if by Heaven's indulgent laws,</l>
            <l>His life was made coeval with his cause:</l>
            <l>Too short the full development to see, --</l>
            <l>Just long enough to leave the captive free.</l>
            <l>Like a good hour-glass, faithful as he ran,</l>
            <l>The founder of his question, and the span.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>Oh! wise coincidence, most kindly given</l>
            <l>"That all may see the power that comes from Heaven."</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>So, when young Wolfe maintained his country's cause,</l>
            <l>Far from his mother-land, in distant wars,</l>
            <l>Though trophied heralds swept across the main,</l>
            <l>They came with tidings of the hero -- slain.</l>
            <l>So, the gale told which brought Trafalgar's fame,</l>
            <l>That naught remained of Nelson -- but a name.</l>
            <l>So, on Coruña's height we found relief --</l>
            <l>So, on Coruña's height we left a chief.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>Turn we from arms. -- What time awakened zeal</l>
            <l>For Afric's sufferings first began to feel,</l>
            <l>When that bad commerce o'er the Atlantic ran</l>
            <l>And impious man presumed to trade in man:</l>
            <l>Our eldest triumph had to shed a tear;</l>
            <l>And Fox's laurels but adorned his bier.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>'Twas from those lips inspired with love of kind,</l>
            <l>By genius kindled, and by art refined, --</l>
            <l>'Twas from that tongue which Senates loved so well,</l>
            <l>Binding the prostrate audience like a spell, --</l>
            <l>'Twas from that heart, which pure and unconfined,</l>
            <l>Let loose the fervid virtues of his mind, --</l>
            <l>That British Statesmen first were taught to see</l>
            <l>That man -- whate'er his colour -- must be free.</l>
            <l>Him, distant lands, and rival nations saw,</l>
            <l>The noble founder of the noblest law, --</l>
            <l>To Sidney's faith he Somers' lore allied,</l>
            <l>And both with warm philanthropy applied --</l>
            <l>In Russel's course we saw him strong to run,</l>
            <l>Great Chatham's true and undegenerate son.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>Yet the same year that gave him power to save,</l>
            <l>Gave him, alas! -- a statue and a grave.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>Then weep no more, -- but gayer numbers call,</l>
            <l>'Tis thus that heroes and that statesmen fall.</l>
            <l>That life is best, which Heaven to each allots --</l>
            <l>That space is long enough, which has no blots.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>So thought the Christian. -- "I have lived," he cried,</l>
            <l>(Mark, oh! ye readers, how the just man died!)</l>
            <l>"What though my day wanes fast -- my life-blood fails --</l>
            <l>"And all within me, but my spirit, quails --</l>
            <l>"I've lived to see my country cast away</l>
            <l>"The unjustest traffic in the justest way!"</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>It was enough -- him, -- nor the storied urn, --</l>
            <l>Nor lamps that with Arabian fragrance burn --</l>
            <l>Him -- nor the sculptor's art, or painter's fame,</l>
            <l>Can raise -- or take a cypher from his name.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <lg>
            <l>But when in after times the Niger pours</l>
            <l>A righteous commerce o'er enfranchised shores,</l>
            <l>Wide as the poles asunder, in renown,</l>
            <l>His name shall travel as an heir-loom down:</l>
            <l>His scroll -- the names of nations unenslaved;</l>
            <l>His monument -- the myriads that he saved.</l>
         </lg>
         
         <signed>
            <l><hi rend="smallcaps">John Parker</hi>.</l>
         </signed>
         <dateline>
            <hi rend="italic">Woodthorpe, near Sheffield</hi>.
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nov</hi>. 20, 1833.
         </dateline>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
