<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Preface</title>
            <author>Mary Anne Rawson</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital text edited by</resp>
               <persName>Christopher Ohge</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>The Bow in the Cloud; or the Negro's Memorial</edition>
            <editor>Mary Anne Rawson</editor>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Jackson &amp; Walford</publisher>
            <pubPlace>St Paul's Churchyard, London</pubPlace>
            <date when="1834">1834</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc> <!-- source below is the copy text manuscript -->
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>University of Manchester</institution>
                  <repository>John Rylands Library</repository>
                  <collection>Rawson/Wilson Anti-slavery Papers</collection>
                  <idno>English MS 415/199</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="prose">
            <p>&quot;T<hi rend="small-caps">he</hi> sorrowful sighing of the
            prisoner&quot; has long come up into the ear of Him who &quot;regards the prayer of the
            destitute.&quot; He hath &quot;heard their voice, and looked on their affliction, and
            their labour, and their oppression;&quot; and, &quot;according to the greatness of his
            power,&quot; he hath ordained that the oppressed should go free. &quot;Not unto us, O
            Lord! not unto us, but unto thy name give glory, for thy mercy and thy truth&#39;s
            sake.&quot;</p> 
            <p>The storms which have so long obscured the face of the heavens are
               departing, and brightening scenes and fairer prospects are opening to view -- the Bow
               is set in the Cloud; it is the memorial of mercy, the pledge of peace. </p>
               
            <p>At such a period, the appearance of a volume, partly illustrative of the evils of
               Slavery, may seem to demand an explanation. </p>
            
            <p>This little Work was projected more than seven years ago, when the state of affairs
               rendered it in the highest degree desirable to engage, by every legitimate effort,
               the thoughts and feelings of the British nation on this momentous question. To the
               Editor&#39;s friends the causes which prevented its immediate publication are known:
               to strangers the detail would be intrusive and uninteresting. The valuable papers
               then kindly furnished, are now presented to the public, with many additional articles
               composed at later periods. They are, for the most part, arranged in the order in
               which they have been received. The pieces commemorative of the Abolition of the
               System will therefore be found towards the close of the volume: those referring to
               the former State of the Slave occupy the earlier pages.</p>
            <p>To those
               readers who, at first sight, may think that the papers written before the abolition
               of the system are now out of date and should have been suppressed, the Compiler
               ventures to suggest, that, even if the appointed apprenticeship of four and six years
               were already expired, yet the past sorrows of the Negro, and the long-continued
               apathy of the nation in disregarding his bitter griefs, should be ever remembered
               with deep humility before God.&quot; We have been verily guilty concerning our
               brother, in that we saw the anguish of his soul, when he besought us, and we would
               not hear.&quot; </p><p>And, though Slavery is banished by legislative
               enactment from the British colonies, over many parts of the globe it still exerts its
               cruel influence. &quot;Slavery, wherever it exists, is the same moral deformity,--
               the same crime before God, and ought to be viewed with detestation, and reprobated
               with boldness, by every man who professes to act on christian principles . . . . Not
               less than FIVE MILLIONS of our fellow creatures are still detained in hopeless bond
               age by the avarice and cruelty of man. . . . There is too much reason to believe,
               that the extensive trade still carried on in the French, Spanish, and Portuguese
               colonies, is sustained by British capital, and screened by British ingenuity. In Cuba
               and the Brazils, and in some of the French colonies, the market for human cattle is
               daily supplied from the coast of Africa; while the mines of Chili and Peru are
               peopled with miserable, though guiltless, victims, whose blood is drained by a system
               of unparalleled horror, to fill the pockets of English shareholders!&quot;<note type="authorial" resp="#MAR">See Stuart's "Three Years in America,"--a work of acknowledged accuracy.</note>Upwards of two millions of unhappy negroes are doomed to suffer the
               brand and curse of slavery, in its most degraded form, in the United States of
               America, -- that land of boasted freedom, while the condition of the free people of
               colour, whose number exceeds 300,000, is only in a slight degree advanced.<note type="authorial" resp="#MAR">See the admirable address of the "Agency Society for the Universal Abolition of Negro Slavery and the Slave Trade throughout the world."
               </note> And though the notice may appear somewhat incongruous in a work
               especially relating to Negro Slavery, the Editor cannot forbear to allude to the
               noble-minded Poles, dying beneath the weight of another species of thraldom, if
               possible, still more galling. For these, prayer should not be omitted, nor should
               effort be restrained. </p><p>And even as regards the British colonies the work
               of mercy is yet imperfect. The personal emancipation of the Negro cannot be regarded
               as the full amount of his powerful and peculiar claims. A debt is still owing him,
               which can only be discharged by combined and persevering effort, prompted by the
               benevolence, and regulated by the wisdom, which are from above; and happily, by these
               means the debt can be discharged, and that abundantly. Having in times past been
               rendered vile, he must now be elevated in the scale of being, by means of moral and
               religious instruction. Let the &quot;glad tidings of great joy, which are unto all
               people,&quot; be sounded in the ears of these despised ones, and let them be made
               acquainted with that freedom wherewith Christ can make them free. Blessed be God!
               multitudes of these wretched outcasts have already heard the joyful sound, and the
               hope of Heaven has shed light and peace along their dreary path;<note type="authorial" resp="#MAR">See the interesting and encouraging Reports of the Baptist, Moravian, and Methodist Missionary Societies.
               </note>May the recital of the wrongs and sufferings of the Slave, contained
               in this volume, excite to greatly increased exertions in this blessed work, and thus
               may the Lord turn the curse into a blessing! </p><p>To those talented and
               esteemed individuals to whose friendly aid this little work is indebted for its
               existence, the most sincere thanks are offered, though with a conscious ness that
               such expressions of gratitude can be of little value. Although they wrote, doubtless,
               from the deep interest which the subject inspired, yet the Editor feels a personal
               obligation to have been conferred by the very obliging manner in which their
               contributions have been presented. </p><p>It would indeed have been delightful
               if every hand which has been actively engaged in pulling down the prison-house, and
               striking off the fetters of the bondman, could have put a stone into the monument
               here erected upon its ruins, to tell posterity where it stood, the curses it
               contained, and how it fell. To many, who have laboured long, and nobly, and
               successfully in this cause, the Editor had no means of access; to others,
               acknowledgments are due for the kind interest they have expressed in the plan and
               success of a work which various circumstances have prevented them from aiding. It is
               a subject for thankfulness that so many have assisted in raising this memorial,
               which, though small in its dimensions and humble in its design, the Compiler believes
               will be found a structure of moral and literary architecture, in some degree worthy
               of the great occasion. </p><p>Nothing is inserted in these pages which was not
               presented to the Editor expressly for the purpose; though, on account of the delay
               that has occurred, it is feared that a few of the papers may have appeared in print
               in other forms. </p><p>There may possibly, on some points, be slight
               differences of opinion between the various writers in this little volume; it is,
               therefore, desirable to remark, that the authors are responsible only for the pieces
               to which their names are appended. </p><p>Some of the allusions to the West
               Indian planters may be considered unwarrantably harsh. It must not for a moment be
               supposed that reference is made to those amiable and respectable persons in this
               country who have had the misfortune to inherit colonial property. The majority of the
               resident planters--the attorneys--the managers are here intended. If the records of
               the &quot;Colonial Church Union,&quot; and many of the Speeches in the Jamaica House
               of Assembly are consulted, it can scarcely be said that any language is too severe.
            </p><p>Should this little volume in any degree contribute to sustain and prolong
               the sympathy of late so widely excited in behalf of the deeply-injured negroes, the
               authors of the following pieces, and the individual who has now the pleasure of
               presenting them to the public, will indeed have reason to rejoice together, and every
               benevolent reader may share in that joy. </p>
            <p><hi rend="small-caps"><placeName>Wincobank Hall</placeName>,</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic"><date when="1834-05-08">May 8, 1834</date></hi>.</p> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
