<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Repose for the Weary</title>
            <author>J. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>The Bow in the Cloud: A Digital Scholarly Edition</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Published in the Bow in the Cloud (1834), pp. 239–40.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <epigraph>
               <quote>"There the wicked cease from troubling, and there the weary be at rest. There the prisoners rest together; they hear not the voice of the oppressor. The small and great are there; and the servant is free from his master."</quote>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>There is a spot within the Western isle,</l>
               <l>Where all is peace and freedom, and the Slave</l>
               <l>In that small lone enclosure finds a home.</l>
               <l>Its sods are paved with monuments, which tell</l>
               <l>The name of him whose bondage here is cancelled,</l>
               <l>And the birth-day of the free. Here is kept</l>
               <l>The charter of the injured Indian's rights,</l>
               <l>Which none dare violate; and he whose name</l>
               <l>Midst freedom's archives here is registered,</l>
               <l>A title to his liberty obtains,</l>
               <l>The proud oppressor never questions more.</l>
               <l>The sugar-cane may never flourish here,</l>
               <l>The soil of this pure sanctuary to taint,</l>
               <l>And mark the Negro's curse; but rosemary</l>
               <l>And thyme, and here and there a violet,</l>
               <l>Adorn each narrow dwelling. Sweetly sleeps</l>
               <l>The free inhabitant; nor hears he more</l>
               <l>The voice of the task-master or the chain.</l>
               <l>On this retreat the worm alone intrudes;</l>
               <l>Yet his still inroads cannot break the sleep</l>
               <l>Of the oppressed sweetly slumbering there.</l>
               <l>From earthly wrong here all may refuge find,</l>
               <l>And undisturbed repose, where softly lie,</l>
               <l>By dreams unstartled, on one balmy couch,</l>
               <l>And by the same light canopy o'ershadowed,</l>
               <l>The proud oppressor with his toil-worn slave.</l>
               <l>And though with penury and scorn o'ercome,</l>
               <l>Each in his turn the ransom pays in full.</l>
               <l>But yet that claim of purchase to receive,</l>
               <l>The oppressor grudges, sickening at the sight</l>
               <l>Of that which buys it, e'en as though the touch</l>
               <l>Would breed corruption; -- for its price is <hi rend="italic">death</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
            <signed>J. R.</signed>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
