<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Voice from the Land of Bondage</title>
            <author>Sarah Joanna Williams</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Mary Anne Rawson's The Bow in the Cloud (1834): A Digital Scholarly Edition</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Published in the Bow in the Cloud, pp. 318–20.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lg>
            <l>A sound arose, -- the voice of ancient wrong,</l>
            <l>Like rushing mighty waters, or the wind</l>
            <l>Sweeping through those old woods, that echoed long</l>
            <l>Wailings, until they left a voice behind,</l>
            <l>And thus it spake --</l>
            <l>"Think ye that slavery, which can conform</l>
            <l>Man to the image of a brute, doth bring</l>
            <l>'Neath its dominion but the outward form?</l>
            <l>In limb and sinews only hath he been</l>
            <l>The bruised, broken reed which ye have seen?</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>"Think ye, your ancestors, when first they brought</l>
            <l>To these fair isles the curse of slavery,</l>
            <l>Merely some links of brass and iron wrought</l>
            <l>Into a chain? Can your state policy,</l>
            <l>As hammers on the anvil, at one stroke</l>
            <l>Sever the fetters they imposed, and give</l>
            <l>To those who once have passed beneath the yoke,</l>
            <l>And learnt but as another's tool to live,</l>
            <l>The hearts, the minds, the feelings of the free,</l>
            <l>The elevating thoughts that wait on Liberty?</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>"Those they oppressed have spirits; -- can ye there</l>
            <l>Trace where the iron entered? Can ye see</l>
            <l>All that came with those chains, of which they were</l>
            <l>Only the emblems, the mere imagery?</l>
            <l>The mandates of your senates cannot reach</l>
            <l>The bands impalpable that chain the soul, --</l>
            <l>Fear, superstition, ignorance; nor teach</l>
            <l>The mind to break at once from their control:</l>
            <l>A higher power these evils must dispel,</l>
            <l>'Tis yours the teachings of that power to tell.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>"'Come unto me, all ye that labour, come</l>
            <l>Ye heavy-laden, I will give you rest.'</l>
            <l>It is the import of these words brought home</l>
            <l>Unto the spirit, maketh it possess'd</l>
            <l>Of all that sanctifieth liberty;</l>
            <l>Soft as refreshing gales breathe forth that word,</l>
            <l>As music o'er the waters let it be,</l>
            <l>Here then in blessings will your names be heard:</l>
            <l>How beautiful the feet of those who bring</l>
            <l>Glad tidings to a heart long suffering!</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>"Deliverance to the slave! What heart now cold,</l>
            <l>What spirits mingled with the holy dead,</l>
            <l>Have throbbed, have toiled, and struggled to behold</l>
            <l>The moment when that mandate should be read:</l>
            <l>Ye who have entered to their labours, ye</l>
            <l>Who reap what they have sown, to you appears</l>
            <l>The dawn, and blessed are your eyes which see</l>
            <l>The light, theirs sought with weariness and tears:</l>
            <l>Now be their names your watch-word -- be ye still</l>
            <l>Fervent, the work of glory to fulfil.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>"'Tis something glorious to civilize</l>
            <l>Beings, whose powers have to themselves been lost,</l>
            <l>To teach the expanding faculties to prize</l>
            <l>Science, and all her pleasure-yielding host;</l>
            <l>'Tis more, to give an anchor to the soul,</l>
            <l>Steadfast and sure; to guide its course aright</l>
            <l>By love, that would be mighty to control,</l>
            <l>Shewn by example in its holiest light:"</l>
            <l>Oh! that a thrilling voice like this might come,</l>
            <l>From those far isles, and reach us in our home.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>There, though oppression long hath shed its blight,</l>
            <l>And made all light unto the spirit dim,</l>
            <l>Friends of the Negro! Lo! "The fields are white</l>
            <l>Already to the harvest. Pray ye Him</l>
            <l>Who is the Lord of harvests, to send forth</l>
            <l>Labourers into the harvest." May His peace</l>
            <l>Rest on that long-polluted spot of earth,</l>
            <l>Making all cruelty and strife to cease.</l>
            <l>Late, tyrants claimed its people as their own,</l>
            <l>Now, may they be our God's, and His alone!</l>
         </lg>
         <byline>
            <persName ref="../personography.xml#williams_sj">S. J. W.</persName>
         </byline>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
