<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prosopography: Bow in the Cloud digital edition</title>
            <editor>Christopher Ohge</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Mary Anne Rawson's The Bow in the Cloud: a scholarly edition and network analysis</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is a born-digital authority file of biographical details relating to the Bow in the Cloud manuscript archive (English MS 414 and 415, John Rylands Library, Manchester, UK).</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <listPerson>
            
            <person xml:id="abney_e">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q76154758">
                  <surname>Abney</surname>
                  <forename type="first">Edward</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">Henry</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1811</birth>
               <death>1892</death>
               <sex>Male</sex>
               <faith>Anglican</faith>
               <note>Edward Henry Abney (1811-1892), domestic chaplain to 1st Baron Belper, was vicar of St. Alkmund's, Derby, afterwards prebendary of Lichfield.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="barton_b">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/47543211">
                  <surname>Barton</surname>
                  <forename>Bernard</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1784</birth>
               <death>1849</death>
               <faith>Quaker</faith>
               <sex>Male</sex>
               <note>Bernard Barton was a Quaker poet who was best known for The Convict's Appeal (1818), in which he protested against the death penalty and the severity of the criminal code.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="benson_m">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29881923">
                  <surname>Benson</surname>
                  <forename>Maria</forename>
               </name>
               <sex>Female</sex>
               <note>Maria Benson was a British writer. She is the author of a few published novels and the pedagocial essay Thoughts on Education. Benson's sister was Anna Dorothea Montagu -- third wife of Basil Montagu (source: https://snaccooperative.org/view/50169953).</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="barnard_ew">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q5345890">
                  <surname>Barnard</surname>
                  <forename>Edward</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">William</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1791</birth>
               <death>1828</death>
               <sex>Male</sex>
               <faith>Anglican</faith>
               <note>Edward William Barnard was a divine, poet and scholar. Nephew of fellow abolitionist, the Archdeacon Francis Wrangham. 'He was educated at Harrow and Trinity College, owing to his distaste for mathematics. In 1817 he published anonymously, 'Poems, founded upon the Poems of Meleager,' which were re-edited in 1818 under the title of 'Trifles, imitative of the Chaster Style of Meleager.' The latter volume was dedicated to Thomas Moore, who tells us in his journal that he had the manuscript to look over, and describes the poems as 'done with much elegance.' Barnard was presented to the living of Brantingthorp, Yorkshire, from which is dated his next publication, 'The Protestant Beadsman' (1822), This is described by a writer in 'Notes and Queries' as a 'delightful little volume on the saints and martyrs commemorated by the English church, containing biographical notices of them, and hymns upon each of them.’ Barnard died prematurely on 10 Jan. 1828' (Source: ODNB, <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Dictionary_of_National_Biography,_1885-1900/Barnard,_Edward_William">https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Dictionary_of_National_Biography,_1885-1900/Barnard,_Edward_William</ref>.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="bowring_j">
               <name ref="https://btw.wlv.ac.uk/authors/1138">
                  <surname>Bowring</surname>
                  <forename>John</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1792</birth>
               <death>1872</death>
               <note>Sir John Bowring was the 4th Governor of Hong Kong and a hymnwriter and translator.
               </note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="bridges_m">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q18093862">
                  <surname>Bridges</surname>
                  <forename>Matthew</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1800</birth>
               <death>1894</death>
               <note>Matthew Bridges was a British-Canadian hymnodist.</note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="brown_jb">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61925237">
                  <surname>Brown</surname>
                  <forename type="first">James</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">Baldwin</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1785</birth>
               <death>1843</death>
               <note><p>[<ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Dictionary_of_National_Biography,_1885-1900/Brown,_James_Baldwin_(1785-1843)">From the Dictionary of National Biography, 1885-1900, Volume 07</ref>:] miscellaneous writer, was called to the bar at the Inner Temple in 1816, and practised on the northern circuit and at the Lancashire quarter sessions. He was appointed judge of the Oldham court of requests in 1840, and died in November 1843. Brown married a sister of the Rev. Thomas Raffles, D.D., and was father of the Rev. James Baldwin Brown [q. v.] His portrait has been engraved.</p> 
                  <p>He was the author of:</p>
                  <p>'An Historical Account of the Laws enacted against the Catholics, both in England and Ireland,' London, 1813, 8vo.
                  <lb/>'An Historical Inquiry into the ancient Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction of the Crown,' 1815, 8vo.
                  <lb/>'Poems' in conjunction with the Rev. Thomas Raffles and Jeremiah Holmes-Wiffen, 1815, 8vo.
                  <lb/>'Memoirs of the Public and Private Life of John Howard, the Philanthropist,' London, 1818, 4to, 2nd edit. 1823, 8vo; dedicated to William Wilberforce, M.P.</p></note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="bulmer_a">
               <name ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/306133896/">
                  <surname>Bulmer</surname>
                  <surname type="maiden">Collinson</surname>
                  <forename>Agnes</forename>
               </name>
               <birth><date when="1775">1775</date>
               <placeName>London</placeName></birth>
               <death><date when="1836">1836</date></death>
               <faith>Wesleyan Methodist</faith>
               <note>Born in London, Bulmer was a poet who belonged to the Wesleyan community, having been admitted by <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q349070">Charles Wesley</ref> himself. Her major publications include <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Mrs. Mortimer</hi> and a 12-book epic poem entitled <hi rend="italic">Messiah's Kingdom</hi> (1833). This poem, consisting of nearly fourteen thousand verses, is one of the longest works of poetry composed by a woman. See also the <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q16147344">Wikidata item</ref> and Andrew O. Winckles' 'The Book of Nature and the Methodist Epic: Agnes Bulmer's Analogic Poetics and the End(s) of Romanticism' <hi rend="italic">Womens Writing</hi> 22:2 (2015), pp. 209–28,
                   (<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09699082.2015.1011841">https://doi.org/10.1080/09699082.2015.1011841</ref>).</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="burchell_t">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7788037">
                  <surname>Burchell</surname>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1799</birth>
               <death>1846</death>
               <faith>Baptist</faith>
               <note>
                  Thomas Burchell was a leading Baptist missionary and slavery abolitionist in Montego Bay, Jamaica, in the early nineteenth century.
               </note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="buxton_tf">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12306089">
                  <surname>Buxton</surname>
                  <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">Fowell</forename>
               </name>
               <birth when="1786">1786</birth>
               <death when="1845">1845</death>
               <note>Sir Thomas Fowell Buxton, 1st Baronet Buxton of Belfield and Runton (1 April 1786 – 19 February 1845) was an English Member of Parliament, brewer, abolitionist and social reformer. In 1822 he succeeded William Wilberforce as leader of the campaign in the House of Commons for the abolition of slavery in the British colonies and thus was partly responsible for the Abolition Act of 28 August 1833.</note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="conder_e">
               <name>
                  <surname>Conder</surname>
                  <forename>Eliza</forename>
               </name>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cunningham_a">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2062341">
                  <surname>Cunningham</surname>
                  <forename>Allan</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1784</birth>
               <death>1842</death>
               <note>Allan Cunngingham was a Scottish poet.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="douglas_j">
               <name ref="https://digital.nls.uk/histories-of-scottish-families/archive/95281787?mode=transcription">
                  <surname>Douglas</surname>
                  <forename>James</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1790</birth>
               <death>1861</death>
               <faith>Congregationalist</faith>
               <note>James Douglas, of Cavers, Scotland, came from a long line of Scottish nobles dating back to Sir James Douglas, who fought with Robert the Bruce during the Scottish Wars of Independence. Douglas was the eighteenth in descent from Archibald, second son of James, second Earl of Douglas, who was killed at the battle of Otterburn, 21st July, 1388. He was born on 9 October 1790 at Cavers, near Hawick, Roxburghshire, and died there on 17 August 1861. He became laird of Cavers on the death of his father in 1815. He published on philosophy, religion, politics and history, and was a staunch opponent of slavery. In 1833 he published his 'Address on Slavery' (Edinburgh: Adam and Charles Black; and London: Longman, Rees, Orme, Brown, Green and Longman, 1833), which argued for the economic costs of slavery and empire. His intention was to broaden the appeal to those who could oppose slavery on utilitarian rather than moral principles.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="edmeston_j">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/19298317">
                  <surname>Edmeston</surname>
                  <forename>James</forename> 
               </name>
               <birth>1791</birth>
               <death>1867</death>
               <faith>Anglican</faith>
               <note>James Edmeston was a British architect, surveyor, and well-known hymnwriter. Edmeston published <hi rend="italic">The Search, and other Poems</hi> in 1817.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="ely_j">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q55020582">
                  <surname>Ely</surname>
                  <forename>John</forename>
               </name>
               <birth when="1793">1793</birth>
               <death when="1847">1847</death>
               <faith>Congregationalist</faith>
               <note>John Ely (1793–1847) was a minister from Leeds. He was educated at Hoxton Academy (London), which was a training institution for dissenting Congregational ministers. Ely served as a pastor in various locations, including Rochdale before moving to Leeds. His work and influence were significant in the religious life of Leeds, particularly in the context of the Congregational movement, which emphasized independent, self-governing congregations outside the established Church of England​ (source: <ref target="https://www.genuki.org.uk/big/eng/YKS/WRY/Leeds/Leeds-SalemChapelCongChurch">https://www.genuki.org.uk/big/eng/YKS/WRY/Leeds/Leeds-SalemChapelCongChurch</ref>)​.</note>
               <!-- need to find more info -->
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gurney_jj">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q6284410">
                  <surname>Gurney</surname>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname>John</surname>
               </name>
               <birth>1788</birth>
               <death>1847</death>
               <note>British banker.</note>
               <!-- complete -->
            </person>
            
            
            <person xml:id="hill_r">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q9310294">
                  <surname>Hill</surname>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1795</birth>
               <death>1872</death>
               <note>Richard Hill (1795-1872) was a Jamaican lawyer, zoologist, politician, and poet, as well as leader of the free people of colour, which campaigned for equal rights in the early nineteenth century.e</note>
            </person>
            <!-- needs more investigation -->
            <person xml:id="hill_th">
               <name>
                  <surname>Hill</surname>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
               </name>
               <note>The Reverend Thomas Hill was the deacon of Chesterfield.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="holland_j">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q15452389">
                  <surname>Holland</surname>
                  <forename>John</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1794</birth>
               <death>1872</death>
               <faith>Methodist</faith>
               <note>John Holland (14 March 1794–28 December 1872) was an English poet, newspaper editor, and writer on mining, botany, geology, topography and metallurgy. Born on the grounds of the ancient Sheffield Manor, in Yorkshire, he published poems as a young man that caught the attention of James Montgomery.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="morpeth">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2079517">
                  <surname>Howard</surname>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <forename>Frederick</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1802</birth>
               <death>1865</death>
               <faith>Anglican</faith>
               <note>George Howard, 7th Earl of Carlisle (1802-1865), known as Lord or Viscount Morpeth in the Bow in the Cloud, was a Whig politician, orator, and writer. He was closely associated with a group of Whig Liberal Anglicans who opposed the Evangelical movement. He also exchanged sonnets with William Wordsworth.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="howitt_m">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42648131">
                  <surname type="married">Howitt</surname>
                  <surname type="maiden">Botham</surname>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1799</birth>
               <death>1888</death>
               <note>Best known for her children's poem 'The Spider and the Fly' (1829), Howitt also painted and translated Hans Christian Anderson...</note>
               <!-- complete -->
            </person>
            <person xml:id="howitt_w">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/22908301">
                  <surname>Howitt</surname> 
                  <forename>William</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1792</birth>
               <death>1879</death>
               <faith>Quaker</faith>
               <note>William Howitt was a Quaker writer and activist. In 1821 he married Mary Botham.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="james_pm">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7152575">
                  <surname>James</surname>
               <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
               <forename type="middle">Moon</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1780</birth>
               <death>1854</death>
               <note>Paul Moon James was a British poet and banker.</note>
               
            </person>
            <!-- ... -->
            <person xml:id="knibb_w">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q8014079">
                  <surname>Knibb</surname> 
                  <forename>William</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1803</birth>
               <death>1845</death>
               <note>William Knibb was a Baptist minister and missionary in Jamaica.</note>
            </person>
            
            <!-- Not sure about this one. There was a Revd Richard Miles who was associated with the London Missionary Society and worked in South Africa in the 1820s. -->
            <person xml:id="miles_r">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7327809">
                  <surname>Miles</surname>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
               </name>
               <note>Richard Miles was a Motswana (Tswana) catechist and preacher "to the native tribes beyond the border" in South Africa.</note>
            </person>
            
            
            <person xml:id="montgomery_j">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/183634">
                  <surname>Montgomery</surname>
                  <forename>James</forename>
               </name>
               <birth when="1771">1771</birth>
               <death when="1854">1854</death>
               <faith>Moravian</faith>
               <note>James Montgomery was a Scottish-born hymn writer, poet, editor, and activist who eventually settled in Sheffield. He was the eldest son of a Moravian clergyman, and was born at Irvine, Scotland, on 4 November 1771. His father was a Moravian pastor and missionary and Montgomery was educated at the Moravian school at Fulneck, near Leeds. He was the editor of the Sheffield Iris newspaper from 1794 to 1825, and was twice imprisoned in the 1790s for publishing articles critical of the authorities. He authored The Wanderer of Switzerland (1807), a poem severely criticised in the Edinburgh Review (Southey sympathised). He also wrote the anti-slavery poem The West Indies (1809) and a series of long historical epics, including Greenland (1819). Southey admired much about Montgomery’s verse (a feeling he shared with Byron), and Southey and Montgomery were occasional correspondents.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="parker_j">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q6251908">
                  <surname>Parker</surname>
                  <forename>John</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1799</birth>
               <death>1881</death>
               <faith>Anglican</faith>
               <note>John Parker (21 October 1799 – 5 September 1881) was an English Whig politician and barrister. He was instrumental in the enfranchisement of Sheffield, petitioning Parliament in 1817 and 1822, and creating a pamphlet stating the case for Sheffield in 1830. When the Sheffield constituency was finally created as a Parliamentary borough in 1832 he was elected alongside James Silk Buckingham as its first MPs. He served as MP for Sheffield until 1852, becoming Lord of the Treasury (1839–1840), First Secretary of the Admiralty, joint Secretary to the Treasury (1846–1849), and a Member of the Privy council (1853).</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="pringle-t">
               <name>
                  <surname>Pringle</surname>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
               </name>
               <birth when="1789-01-05">5 January 1789</birth>
               <death when="1834-12-05">5 December 1834</death>
               <note>was a Scottish writer, poet and abolitionist. Known as the father of South African poetry, he was the first successful English language poet and author to describe South Africa's scenery, native peoples, and living conditions (source: Wikipedia).</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="pritchard_jwh">
               <name>
                  <surname>Pritchard</surname>
                  <forename>J. W. H.</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1804?</birth>
               <death>1836</death>
               <faith>Congregationalist</faith>
               <note>Reverend J. W. H. Pritchard was a congregationalist minister. In 1826 he published a life of his predecessor. He died 14th July, 1836, at 32.</note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rawson_ma">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/4004154867602660100003">
                  <surname>Rawson</surname>
                  <forename>Mary Anne</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1801</birth>
               <death>1887</death>
               <sex>Female</sex>
               <faith>Congregationalist</faith>
               <note>Mary Anne Rawson was an abolitionist and activist. She campaigned with the Tract Society and the British and Foreign Bible Society, for Italian nationalism, and against child labour. She was first involved as a founding member of the Sheffield Ladies Anti-Slavery group, which successfully campaigned for people to boycott sugar from the West Indies, as it was produced by slave labour.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="rawson_tt">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/26896473">
                  <surname>Taylor</surname>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">Rawson</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1807</birth>
               <death>1835</death>
               <sex>Male</sex>
               <faith>Congregationalist</faith>
               <note>Congregationalist minister.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="roscoe_j">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/74211865">
                  <surname type="married">Hornblower</surname>
                  <surname type="maiden">Roscoe</surname>
                  <forename type="middle">Elizabeth</forename>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1797</birth>
               <death>1853</death>
               <sex>Female</sex>
               <faith>Unitarian</faith>
               <note>Jane E. Roscoe was a poet. She was the daughter of the abolitionist MP William Roscoe (1753–1831) and Jane Roscoe (née Griffies). In 1838 she married the Unitarian minister Francis Hornblower (1812–1853). Her <hi rend="italic">Poems by one of the Authors of Poems for Youth by a Family Circle</hi> were published in 1820, and her <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> in 1843 Her hymns in common use are:—
                  
                  1. How rich the blessings, O my God. Gratitude. In the Liverpool Kenshaw Street Collection 1818.
                  2. My Father, when around me spread. Peace in Affliction. Appeared in the Monthly Repository, Dec, 1828; and the Sacred Offering, 1832.
                  3. O God, to Thee, Who first hast given. Self-Consecration. In Poems for Youth, 1820.
                  4. Thy will be done, I will not fear. Resignation.
                  [Rev. Valentine D. Davis, B.A.]
                  
                  (John Julian, Dictionary of Hymnology (1907).)
                  
Sister of William Stanley Roscoe; Elizabeth Roscoe; Edward Roscoe; James Roscoe; Robert Roscoe; Thomas Roscoe; Richard Roscoe; Mary Anne Jevons and Henry Roscoe.</note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="sterndale_mh">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61410705">
               <surname>Sterndale</surname>
               <forename type="first">Mary</forename>
               <forename type="nee">Handley</forename>
            </name>
               <birth>1766</birth>
               <death>1840</death>
               <sex>Female</sex>
               <note>Mary Handley Sterndale was a poet, novelist, and travel writer. Born in Derbyshire. She became friends with the poet Anna Seward (1742-1809; ODNB). See more at <ref target="https://btw.wlv.ac.uk/authors/1138">https://btw.wlv.ac.uk/authors/1138</ref>.</note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="taylor_a">
               <name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/10688233">
                  <surname>Gilbert</surname>
                  <surname type="maiden">Taylor</surname>
                  <forename>Ann</forename>
               </name>
               <birth when="1782">1782</birth>
               <death when="1866">1866</death>
               <sex>Female</sex>
               <faith>Congregationalist</faith>
               <note>Ann Gilbert (née Taylor) was an English poet and literary critic. She was the daughter of the noncomformist pastor, author, and engraver Isaac Taylor (1759–1829), and second wife of Joseph Gilbert, a Congregationalist minister. She gained lasting popularity in her youth as a writer of verse for children. In the years up to her marriage, she became an astringent literary critic. However, she is best remembered as the elder sister and collaborator of Jane Taylor.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="gilbert_j">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q6283438">
                  <surname>Gilbert</surname>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1779</birth>
               <death>1852</death>
               <sex>Male</sex>
               <faith>Congregationalist</faith>
               <note>Joseph Gilbert (1779–1852) was an Independent then Congregational minister who in 1813 married the renowned children's author Ann Taylor (who also contributed to The Bow in the Cloud).</note>
            </person>
            
            <!-- no info on this one... -->
            <person xml:id="smith_ah">
               <name>
                  <surname>Smith</surname>
                  <forename>A. H.</forename>
               </name>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="taylor_i">
               <name>
                  <surname>Taylor</surname>
                  <forename>Isaac</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1787</birth>
               <death>1865</death>
               <sex>Male</sex>
               <note>English philosopher, writer, artist, and inventor. Brother of Jane and Ann Taylor, and friends with Josiah Conder</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="townley_d">
               <name>
                  <surname type="married">Townley</surname>
                  <surname type="maiden">Ball</surname>
                  <forename>Dinah</forename>
                  <note>Dinah Townley (née Ball) was Mary Anne Rawson's governess and a published poet. She married James Townley, Wesleyan Methodist minister, in 1829. She was also connected to James Montgomery.</note>
               </name>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="townley_j">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q19107008">
                  <surname>Townley</surname>
                  <forename>James</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1774</birth>
               <death>1833</death>
               <faith>Wesleyan Methodist</faith>
               <note>'Wesleyan divine, son of Thomas Townley, a Manchester tradesman, was born at that town on 11 May 1774, and educated by the Rev. David Simpson [q. v.] of Macclesfield. He became a member of the Wesleyan methodist body in 1790, and a minister in 1796. In 1822 he received the degree of D.D. from the college of Princeton, New Jersey, in recognition of his literary work. From 1827 to 1832 he acted as general secretary of the Wesleyan Methodist Missionary Society, and in 1829 was elected president of the Wesleyan conference, and presided at the Dublin and Leeds conferences. While in Manchester he was a member of a philological society founded by Dr. Adam Clarke. He died at Ramsgate on 12 Dec. 1833. He was twice married—to Mary Marsden and Dinah Ball, both of London—and had seven children by his first wife' (Dictionary of National Biography, 1885-1900/Townley, James (1774-1833)).</note>
            </person>
            
            <person>
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q18528740">
                  <surname>Townsend</surname>
                  <forename>Lucy</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>25 July 1781</birth>
               <death>20 April 1847</death>
               <note>Lucy Townsend (née Jesse) was a British abolitionist. She started the first Ladies' Anti-Slavery Society in Birmingham, UK, titled the Birmingham Ladies Society for the Relief of Negro Slaves.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="townshend_c">
               <name>
                  <surname>Townshend</surname>
                  <forename type="first">Chauncey</forename>el
                  <forename type="middle">Hare</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1798</birth>
               <death>1868</death>
               <faith>Anglican</faith>
               <note>Chauncey Hare Townshend (1798–1868) was a poet and collector. He took holy orders in the Church of England as a young man, but was disabled by illness from the active duties of his profession. Early in life he made the acquaintance of Robert Southey, and received an invitation to Greta Hall, Southey's residence in the vale of Keswick. Encouraged by the laureate's approbation, he published a volume of ‘Poems’ in 1821 (London, 8vo) which were generally praised. He also became friends with Charles Dickens, owing to his interest in mesmerism.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="walker_e">
               <name ref="https://www.geni.com/people/Elizabeth-Abney/6000000204883880265">
                  <surname>Walker</surname>
                  <forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">Abney</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1782</birth>
               <death>1850</death>
               <note>Elizabeth Walker was a poet and activist and wife of Henry Walker (1785-1860), an iron and steel businessman from Rotherham (see <ref target="https://www.cliftonpark.org.uk/homepage/29/the-walkers-of-clifton-house">https://www.cliftonpark.org.uk/homepage/29/the-walkers-of-clifton-house</ref>).</note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="watson_j">
               <name ref="https://www.benshamgrove.org.uk/history/the-spence-watsons/">
                  <surname>Watson</surname>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1807</birth>
               <death>1874</death>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wiffen_jh">
               <name>
                  <surname>Wiffen</surname>
                  <forename type="first">Jeremiah</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">Holmes</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1792</birth>
               <death>1836</death>
               <note>Wiffen was a prolific poet and translator. He hailed from an ironmongers family in Woburn, Bedfordshire. With James Baldwin Brown and the Rev. Thomas Raffles, he published a book entitled 'Poems by Three Friends' in 1812. In 1821, John Russell, the (progressive) 6th Duke of Bedford, appointed him the Chief Librarian at Woburn Abbey. He set about writing a history of the Hosue of Russell, translating the Italian poet Tasso, and writing well-regarded poems such as 'On Planting a Slip from Milton’s Mulberry Tree, in the Grounds of Woburn Abbey, Presented by Dr. Thackeray, of Cambridge'. <!-- CHECK? Wiffen had began work on a history of the Russell family.  The research on this, which took him to Normandy for four months, took eight years in total, and the resultant book was the most detailed family history he could compile.  It was published in 1833, as “The Historical Memoirs of the House of Russell”. The Senate House Library, at the University of London, holds 25 pages of manuscript notes of the book, but it breaks off at about 1230AD. A number of engravings are inserted, including seven taken from the large paper edition of the book. -->
             </note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="williams_sj">
               <name ref="https://hymnary.org/person/Williams_SarahJohanna1805">
                  <surname>Williams</surname>
                  <forename type="first">Sarah</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">Joanna</forename> <!-- also seen spelled as 'Johanna' -->
               </name>
               <birth>1805</birth>
               <death>1841</death><!-- could be 1844, per the Rylands, but other sources suggest it's 1841 -->
               <faith>Unitarian</faith>
               <note>Sarah Joanna Williams (1805-1841) was the daughter of Mansfield-based Unitarian minister Rev. John Williams (1768–1835), the biographer of Rev. Thomas Belsham. She contributed various poems to the Liverpool Sacred Offering. In the vol. for 1834 is the poem, "Quiet from God! it cometh not to still The vast and high aspirings of the soul," from which the hymn, “Quiet from God! how blessed 'tis to keep," Rest in God, is adapted in Martineau’s Hymns of Praise and Prayer, also in J. P. Hopp’s Collection.
                  </note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="wrangham_f">
               <name ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q15457452">
                  <surname>Wrangham</surname>
               <forename>Francis</forename>
               </name>
               <birth>1769</birth>
               <death>1842</death>
               <sex>Male</sex>
               <faith>Anglican</faith>
               <note>Classical scholar, writer, and archdeacon</note>
            </person>
         </listPerson>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
