<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Thomas Burchell to Mary Anne Rawson (English MS 414/103)
            </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Transcribed from original text.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <dateline>London Nov 19th 1833</dateline>
            <opener>
               <salute>Respected Madam</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours of the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst I received
               a few days since, requesting the communication of
               one or two facts respecting the Negroes in the Island of
               Jamaica -- I certainly feel considerable difficulty in
               writing a narrative of facts without having some speci-
               fic object in being, or some subject to illustrate -- how-
               ever I will give you the bare relation of two or three inci-
               dents which came under my observation &amp; if you consi-
               der them worthy of a place in your contemplated vo-
               lume, you are at liberty to make what use of them you
               please. Perhaps it will be best for you to take the facts
               &amp; clothe them with your own language so as to promote
               your own purpose &amp; designs &amp; make them suitable for such
               a volume.</p>
            <p>-- You "wish for some fact shewing the readi-
               ness with which Slaves will work for even a small remu-
               neration" -- On this subject you may obtain important
               information in the Evidence of Mr. Taylor contained in the
               Parliamentary Report of the select Comte for the Extinc-
               tion of Slavery -- The following incident also is direct to
               the point &amp; fully proves the disposition of the Slaves to
               labour if they are fairly remunerated -- Wishing to
               widen &amp; improve a road from the highway to my residence
               which was up a steep &amp; difficult ascent &amp; indeed scarcely
               passable, I applied to a Master of a jobbing gang &amp; re-
               quested him to inform me the lowest terms for which
               he would undertake the work; after several interviews
               &amp; discussions, he offered to perform it for the sum of £32
               requiring prompt payment -- Considering this amount
               too high, &amp; it being more than I could afford I was induced
               to pursue another plan -- Accordingly one day I took
               a Slave, who was Driver of a jobbing gang, &amp; after explain-
               ing the nature &amp; difficulties of the work, proposed the fol-
               lowing question -- Supposing I was to hire of Your Master
               12 Negroes, &amp; if instead of working there before the while,
               I gave each one a fippenny* per day besides paying the
               Master**, how many days would they require to complete the work?
               The negro proceeded to examine the nature of the work, when
               after some time he returned &amp; replied that if thus rewarded
               they would do it in 10 days or 11 at the fastest -- Upon this
               information I applied to the Master, &amp; hired the Slaves,
               who were sent to me on the following Monday -- Before however
               appointing them their work, I called them together &amp; addressed
               them in the following manner -- I have hired you of your
               master to perform certain work -- I shall not allow the whip to be
               used or carried by the Driver, but if you turn out early in the
               morning, &amp; work well during the day, I will give each a fippenny
               for himself -- if any one is <hi rend="italic">late</hi> to his work, or indolent in
               his work, I'll not give him any thing, but will send him home
               &amp; obtain another slave in his stead -- When I had thus spoken
               one of the Negroes with much good-humour replied, "Massa
               no you talk about sending we home, give we de hammer &amp;
               make we go, work" -- They proceeded, &amp; I never recollect to
               have seen any persons work better or more cheerfully -- Fre-
            </p>
            <note type="footnote">
               <p>* Fippenny - is a piece of money current in Jam<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></p>
            </note>
            <note type="footnote">
               <p>** The amount charged by the Master for the hire of each Negro was
                  26[?] [?] per day</p>
            </note>
            <p>quently when I went to see how they were getting on, they would
               indulge in these jokes -- "Massa you no send we home yet"! Refer-
               ring to my address to them -- one morning I went down about
               past 5 o'clock, they have been at work about an hour, when with
               much good humour they said -- "Massa, no you say, if Neger
               no turn out soon you send him home? Maybe no use, him
               no know when Neger come" -- And at another time as they
               were breaking the stone for the road, one remarked -- "Massa
               dat fippenny, -- him make de stone break! If de hammer
               only fall upon de stone, him break <hi rend="sub">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">all</hi> to pieces" I had not
               occasion to withhold the promised reward from one, or in-
               deed to find fault with one -- &amp; such was the influence which
               this small sum had upon them that they completed the
               work within the specified time, so that it cost me but
               £13.15 -- instead of £32 -- -- Should you think proper
               to make any use of this fact, you will please <hi rend="italic">not to publish
                  my name</hi>, but acknowledge it as the communication of an
               Individual who was for several years a Resident in Jam<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> --
               I make this request because it is likely I shall soon be re-
               turning to the Island, &amp; of course I am desirous not to occa-
               sion More ill will against myself than at present exists: --
               for the same reason I think it undesirable to relate the
               case of the Negress to whom you refer, as I could not state that
               without severely reflecting upon the Master. And as that fact
               &amp; the parties would be at once recognized &amp; as I shall have to come
               into frequent contact with some of the persons concerned, it
               may do me much injury --</p>
            <p>Respecting the for-
               giving disposition of the Negroes the following circumstance
               will afford convincing demonstration -- You are aware of
               my arrest &amp; imprisonment, as well as that of other Mis-
               sionaries during the sanguinary persecutions of 1831–2 --
               The cruel sufferings inflicted upon many of the Christian Ne-
               groes during that period for their attachment to the Redeem-
               er &amp; his cause can never be fully related; so that had they
               given vent to their feelings by the most indignant expressions
               it could not have excited our surprise; but so far from this,
               I do not remember to have heard one Christian Slave during the
               whole of those cruel persecutions indulge in a vindictive
               term towards any of their malignant oppressors -- &amp; the day
               of my liberation from incarceration, on my arrival at
               my lodgings, crowds of my afflicted friends thronged to
               see me, giving vent to their feelings by their many tears, &amp; their
               kindly expressions of sympathy on account of my suffer-
               ings &amp; congratulations for my triumph over my bitter
               foes who were thirsting for my blood -- Amongst many
               other interesting remarks one poor Christian Negro addressed
               me in the following manner. "Massa" said he "You
               feel too bad. -- We Enemy, -- dem wicked, -- dem bad for true;
               Massa's dem take we <del>Neger</del> Negor, -- dem shoot we, -- den hang
               we -- dem flog we -- dem spill *1 we blood, as tho' we no worth *2 at
               all
               -- but Minister we must pray for dem. Dem very
               bad -- dem very wicked -- but -- <hi rend="small-caps">Dem no convert yet</hi>"!!! A
               noble apology made by one of those despised Slaves on be-
               half of those cruel men, &amp; which cannot but remind us
               of the spirit &amp; prayer of the blessed Redeemer upon the
               Cross "Father forgive them for they know not what they
               do" -- they are not converted yet --</p>
            <p>I must however conclude, as I fear you will con-
               sider me negligent for
               for not having replied earlier, tho&#39;
               I have only received your Letter a few days; and my [...] [<hi rend="italic">rest is missing</hi>]
               * 1. They spill our blood
               * 2. As tho&#39; we were of no value at <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>