<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Thomas Moore to Mary Anne Rawson</title>
            <author>Thomas Moore</author>
            <editor>Christopher M. Ohge</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This is a born-digital diplomatic transcription of an unpublished letter.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>John Rylands Library
                  </repository>
                  <collection>Rawson-Wilson Antislavery Collection</collection>
                  <idno>Eng MS 415-161</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address><addrLine>Sloperton Cottage</addrLine></address>
               <date when="1826-03-24">March 24 1826</date>.
               <salute>Madam</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You do me but justice in supposing that I
               
               <lb/>feel deeply interested in the cause for which you are so laudably
               
               <lb/>exerting yourself; &amp; it gives he great pain to be obliged, from the
               
               <lb/>peculiar circumstances in which I am placed, to withhold the <add place="above">^sort</add> of asis=
               
               <lb/>tance which you do me the honour to think should afford you. Being
               
               <lb/>exposed to a variety of applications of this kind (though for far less
               
               <lb/>interesting purposes) I have been obliged to adopt a general resolution
               
               <lb/>not &amp; contribute to any work of the nature of yours, whatever. In pursu=
               
               <lb/>ance of this determination I was compelled, some time ago, to refuse the
               
               <lb/>request of Dr. Montgomery that I would write something for his work in
               
               <lb/>aid of the Chimney Sweepers -- a work, which both from my admiration
               
               <lb/>of the Editor's genius, and my interest in the benevolent object he had in
               
               <lb/>view, I should have been most happy to assist to the utmost of my power.
               
               <lb/>This will, I trust, be a sufficient apology for the necessity which
               
               <lb/>I find myself under of adopting the same conduct with respect to you.
            </p>
            <closer><salute>I have the honour to be your much
               
              
               <lb/> obliged Servant
               
            </salute>
               <signed>Thomas Moore</signed></closer>
            <postscript><p></p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>