<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Ralph Wardlaw to Mary Anne Rawson (English MS 415/160)
            </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Mary Anne Rawson's The Bow in the Cloud (1834): A Digital Scholarly Edition</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John Rylands Library, Rawson/Wilson Collection, Eng MS 415/160</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter-text">
            <opener>
            <dateline>Edinburgh March 20th, 1834.</dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Madam</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>   
            I am sorry that the apology you
            so kindly meant for me is one which I cannot
            plead -- namely that your first letter might possibly
            not have reached me. At the same time, it would
            be impossible for me, after so long an interval
            to give any distinct account of the circumstances
            which, at the period of its reception, prevented me from
            answering it, I have most assuredly been very ungal-
            lant; and, considering the nature and object of the
            request it contained, in other respects culpable[?].
            Your second letter reached me at Glasgow on the
            afternoon of this day simight[?]; and next morn-
            ing I came off for Edinr. where I now write.
            A press of engagements prevented me from getting any
            thing said in reply before leaving home; and since
            coming in here, I have been tossed about incessant-
            ly. I am tho more concerned at this, because, after
            all I am constrained to answer you in terms that
            will not be to your mind, -- that is, in terms of ne-
            gation. I should not only be seriously[?] anxious to
            gratify you; I should count it, moreover, a high
            honour to have my name associated with the names
            of those eminent and excellent friends of religion
            and humanity, whom you mention; and an hon-
            our still higher to appear in permanent associa-<pb/>
            tion with the Cause, equally glorious for its piety
            and its benevolence, in which they have so nobly
            and through the divine blessing, so successfully
            co-operated. I rejoice in having been, even in how-
            ever feeble a manner, employed in the work of ?
            pecation?, -- in pulling down the prison-house, and
            striking off the fetters of the bondmen; -- and few
            things could afford me a higher gratification than
            to put a stone into the Monument which you are
            engaged in erecting upon its ruins, to tell posterity
            where it stood, the curses it contained, and how
            it fell. But it must not be. The time is alrea-
            dy gone, which your last letter allowed me; and
            my hands are now, and must be for some time
            to come, quite full. I might explain how; but
            it might wear the aspect of affectation, and is un-
            necessary. The hands you inumerall are more than
            sufficient to present to the view of posterity an ex-
            quisite piece of masonry, -- a structure, in moral
            &amp; literary architecture, amply worthy of the great
            occasion. ----
         </p>
         <p>I have only now once more to offer my apolo-
            gies, lame as I feel them to be, for my former long
            silence, and to ask your forgiveness. ----
            Mrs. W. who is here with me, unites[?] in kindest
            regards to youself &amp; to the members of both the fa-
            milies with which you stand connected. -- We are <pb/>
            just going down to Leith, and intend leaving for
            home to morrow morning. -- We thank you for
            your kind regrets as to our not seeing you when in
            your neighbourhood; we join in reciprocating those
            regrets, and hope to be more fortunate next time.
         </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Believe me to be, My Dear Madam<lb/>
               Yours with esteem &amp; affection
               </salute>
            <signed>Ralph Wardlaw</signed>
         </closer></div>
         <div type="envelope">
            <ab type="stamp">
               MAR | 20 E | 1834</ab>
               <ab>Add! 1/2.</ab>
               <ab type="address">Mrs. John Rawson<lb/>
               Mrs.[?] Reid's Esq<lb/>
               Wincobank<lb/>
               near Sheffield
               </ab>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
