<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Thomas Clarkson to Mary Anne Rawson</title>
            <author>Thomas Clarkson</author>
            <editor>Christopher M. Ohge</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This is a born-digital diplomatic transcription of an unpublished letter.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Written on one side of a sheet of wove paper.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address><addrLine><placeName>Playford Hall</placeName></addrLine></address>
               <date when="1833-04-15">April 15 1833</date>
               <salute>Madam</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               To Miss Mary Anne Read
               
               Respected Friend
               
               Your letter of Apl 4th, the date of which
               
               makes me ashamed, should have received a much earlier reply
               
               had it not been for the difficulty I found in fixing my mind
               
               upon a subject, which has already received almost every species
               
               of poetic embellishment, and has been presented to the public in such
               
               a variety of forms. After adopting and discarding various topies, as
               
               corrnected with the general question, the simple form of expression
               
               intich heads the following starvys, occurred to me, and was the
               
               germn from which every other thought proceeded. I could view
               
               Slavery in no other light than that of one continued system
               
               of oppression and tenror, and therefore, have considered it in its
               
               effects, as operating both on matter and mind - on man, in his
               
               health and spirits - on man, as amenable to the civil law, and
               
               as a professing chuistean - operating on every relation of life, whether
               
               civil, domestic, or religious _ and its, tremendous results, in reference
               
               to the just judgments of a ser avenging God. In order to puoduce of
               
               feet, I have anned more at strength than case; and if I shall
               
               have produced any thig capable of imparting either satisfaction
               
               to yourself or aid to the cause, it will be sufficient for me
               
               to know, with the female in the gospel, that though I have
               
               not done what I would, I have done what I could and
               
               that little has been accepted. With christian, regards to the
               
               family, I am
               
               With the utmost Respect
               
               Your Obedt Servant
               
               James Everett
               
               Manchester.
               
               June 14th 1826?
               
               The Reign of Terror.
               
               Away, away, forterror here
               
               resurps an universal reign.
               
               Away, like righteous Lot, in fear
               
               Nor tavry those in all the plain.
               
               Away, for through the Western Isles
               
               Which sprang from occan's bed in smiles
               
               The damon stalks, and claims the whole
               
               Like him who once to Edon stoll
               
               And spread the blight of death.
               
               His music is the victu's cry,
               
               The shrivelling glance is in his eye,
               
               Infection in his breath.
               
               Falk not of joy, where slavery reigns.
               
               Of brightning hopes midst "hope depar'd,
               
               The negro's joys are huny in chains
               
               The negro's hopes are all interr'd:
               </p>
            <closer><salute>I am Madam yours very truly
               
               </salute>
               <signed>Thomas Clarkson</signed></closer>
               <postscript><p></p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
