<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Untitled poem by Elizabeth Walker (English MS 415/134)</title>
            <author>Elizabeth Walker</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Transcribed from original text.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <quote>He hath sent me to heal the broken hearted to preach deliverance to the Captives -- &amp; recovering of sight to the blind to set at liberty them that bruised to preach the acceptable year of the Lord -- Luke 4th chapter 18 &amp; 19th verses</quote>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>Lest! to that deep despairing groan, that frantic cry of woe!</l>
               <l>Gaze on those looks of agony, those scalding tears that flow</l>
               <l>flash! 'tis the clank of Slav'ry's chain, they forge each ? fast</l>
               <l>One parting, hopeless look of love -- Ah! Captive, 'tis thy last!!</l>
               <l>Now swiftly o'er the briny deep the fatal vessel flies,</l>
               <l>No light of day, no breath of Heav'n, to mingle with their sighs</l>
               <l>Unheeded flow those bitter tears, e'en Pity[?] weeps in vain</l>
               <l>Alas! the depth of human woe -- they ne'er will smile again!</l>
               <l>Thro' years of piercing agony, we hear the sad low moan</l>
               <l>or cutting lash, or cruel scourge ??? the deeper groan</l>
               <l>Then mem'ry pictures home, &amp; wife. Ah! can he e'er forget?</l>
               <l>His children too, can they be slaves? More bitter anguish yet?</l>
               <l>Towards Heav'n the clasped hands are raised the woe[?] worn ? eye</l>
               <l>God pity Thee!! poor suff'ring one! from Man no aid is nigh</l>
               <l>Yet cheer, oh cheer thee hapless Slave -- thy Tyrants ? is o'er</l>
               <l>Thou'st hast'ning to that happy Land, where He can set[?] no more</l>
               <l>Th' indignant heart has burst in twain -- its last warm streaming-</l>
               <l>blood</l>
               <l>Appeals from mans base treachery -- to a heart searching[?] God!</l>
               <l>Thou Lord! hast heard the Captives prayers, hast set his Spirit</l>
               <l>free</l>
               <l>Captive, but in the bonds of love, he dwells in bliss with thee!!</l>
               <l>How rouse[?] thee Albions! ah how long has been thy dreamy</l>
               <l>sleep --</l>
               <l>Shall Africs children still be Slaves "still drag those chains</l>
               <l>&amp; weep."</l>
               <l>Britons!! oh Liberty is yours oh Liberty you prize --</l>
               <l>Then claim it, for you fetterd Slave, who now in anguish</l>
               <l>lies --</l>
               <l>A Light, the star of Hope &amp; Joy, has o'er th' Atlantic shone</l>
               <l>Shall it be quench'd in deeper night -- shall Hope's bright</l>
               <l>gleam be gone?</l>
               <l>Ah! no! let ev'ry heart respond -- be firm, press on &amp; prove</l>
               <l>What British hands &amp; hearts can do, when sway'd by</l>
               <l>Christian love!!</l>
            </lg>
           
               <metamark>_______</metamark>
               <signed>Elizabeth</signed>
            <metamark>_______</metamark>
               <postscript><ab>she hath done what she <emph>could</emph>!</ab></postscript>
               <dateline><date when="1833-04-03">April 3rd 1933</date></dateline>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>