<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Leonard Dober</title>
				<author>James Montgomery</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Digital text edited by</resp>
					<persName>Christopher Ohge</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>The Bow in the Cloud; or the Negro's Memorial</edition>
				<editor>Mary Anne Rawson</editor>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Jackson &amp; Walford</publisher>
				<pubPlace>St Paul's Churchyard, London</pubPlace>
				<date when="1834">1834</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc> <!-- below is the ms copy text -->
					<msIdentifier>
						<institution>University of Manchester</institution>
						<repository>John Rylands Library</repository>
						<collection>Rawson/Wilson Anti-slavery Collection</collection>
						<idno>English MS 414-85a</idno>
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head>An Account of the first Introduction of the Gospel among Negro-Slaves in the West-Indies, by Voluntary Christian Missionaries. </head>
				<p>I&lt;span style="small-caps"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; the early part of the last century, a negro&amp;shy; slave, on the Danish island of St. Thomas, fre&amp;shy;quently sat, after the labours of the day, on the sea-shore, and earnestly sighed for a knowledge of the gospel, concerning which he had caught some imperfect notions from the professions of Europeans, though no man cared for his soul, or for the souls of thousands of his fellow-sufferers perishing for lack of knowledge. It was not long after he had fallen into this train of feeling, that his master took him away from the island, and brought him to Copenhagen. There he heard the good tidings of great joy, which are unto all people; he believed them, and was baptized into &amp;nbsp;the death of Jesus, by the name of Anthony. Then, immediately, his soul yearned with affection and sympathy towards his sister whom he had left, a slave in the plantations; and he longed to make her a partaker of the same blessedness which he knew. </p>
				<p>About this time, meeting with some pious companions of Count Zinzendorff, who had arrived at the court of Denmark to attend the coronation of Christian VI., Anthony broke his mind to them, saying, &amp;quot;Oh! that some one would go and preach the gospel to my sister in St. Thomas!&amp;quot; These good persons introduced him to the count, who being a man of gracious manners, and one who from his youth had cherished a hope of sending the gospel to the heathen, hearkened eagerly to the representations of Anthony, that if preachers were sent to the island, not his sister only, but many of the slaves there would gladly receive them, and might in the end be converted from the error of their ways. Count Zinzendorff had lately become the patron of a small body of refugees from Moravia, the remains of the ancient church of the United Brethren, who had found an asylum from persecution on his estate in Lusatia. There, in the midst of a forest, they had built a few humble habitations and a place wherein to worship God in peace, after the manner of their forefathers, who, for centuries, had been &amp;quot;a poor &amp;nbsp;and afflicted people, whose trust was in the Lord;&amp;quot; while from generation to generation they kept up a succession of martyrs and confessors of the truth, amidst the darkness of superstition in their native land. </p>
				<p>On the count&amp;#39;s return to Herrnhut (the new settlement, whose population did not yet exceed six hundred persons), he communicated to the little congregation, at their daily evening meeting in the chapel, what he had learnt in his interview with the converted negro. While he yet spake, the hearts of two of his hearers, &amp;nbsp;Tobias Leopold, burned within them to go forth, and be the messengers of salvation to Anthony&amp;#39;s sister. These young men were inti&amp;shy;mate friends, yet neither of them spake to the other on the subject that night, but cherished the fervent desire, each alone in his own bosom, praying and weeping over it till morning, when they met, and, to their mutual surprise and delight, on comparison found, that &amp;quot;as face answereth to face,&amp;quot; so did the heart of the one to the other, and &amp;quot;as iron sharpeneth iron,&amp;quot; so each sharpened the countenance of his friend. In the evening, while they and others of the young men of the congre&amp;shy;gation were returning from the usual walks which they took in the forest, for private prayer and spiritual converse, Count Zinzendorff was stand&amp;shy;ing at the door of his lodging, in company with &amp;nbsp;the Rev. Mr. Shaeffer, a pious clergyman, who happened to be on a visit at Herrnhut; when, as they passed, two and two, towards their homes, the former turned to the latter, and said, &amp;quot;My dear friend, there are, amongst these brethren, messengers who will go forth to preach the gospel in the West Indies, Greenland, Lapland, and other heathen countries.&amp;quot; This prophetic saying was the more remarkable, because no plan had yet been contemplated, nor was indeed likely to be undertaken, by these christian exiles and emi&amp;shy;grants from various quarters, seeking rest for themselves with liberty of conscience, in that solitary place. Nevertheless, the two friends, who had made up their minds for the service of the Lord among the negroes, were encouraged by that saying to offer themselves for the work, first in a letter privately addressed to the count, and afterwards openly to the congregation. </p>
				<p>In the course of a few weeks the negro, Anthony, himself arrived at Herrnhut, and confirmed, at a public meeting there, all that he had stated at Copenhagen, respecting the wants and the willingness of his ignorant and oppressed country&amp;shy;-men in St. Thomas, to receive the gospel: but, he added, so long and so severely were they worked by their masters, that, unless those who went to preach to them would consent to become slaves themselves, and labour with the negroes in &amp;nbsp;the plantations, they would have little opportu&amp;shy;nity of communicating divine instruction to them. This intelligence did not in the smallest degree daunt the devoted young men; they were both ready, not only to be bound, but to die for the Lord Jesus. Such indeed was the simplicity of purpose, singleness of heart, and strength of faith, by which they were actuated, that they were willing to make any sacrifice which might be required, if they could win but one soul to Christ,--nay, if they might but have the opportunity of carrying the news of salvation to Anthony&amp;#39;s sister,--a poor despised female slave.</p>
				<p>Difficulties, however, with regard to the prac&amp;shy;ticability of the attempt, among their brethren and sisters, whom they were bound to consult and reconcile to it, occasioned the delay of a full year. At length the perplexity of the congrega&amp;shy;tion became so great, that the elders resolved to &amp;quot;cast the lot into the lap,&amp;quot; and leave &amp;quot;the whole disposing thereof&amp;quot; with &amp;quot;the Lord,&amp;quot; (Prov. xvi. 33.) according to the practice then and ever since observed in their church, in the appointment of ministers, and for the decision of other important affairs. Prayer having been made,--out of several scriptural sentences, suitably chosen, &amp;nbsp;the following, &amp;quot;Let the lad go up:&amp;quot; &amp;quot;The Lord is with him.&amp;quot; This put an end to all scruples, and he was forthwith set apart for the missionary enterprise. The faith and patience of his friend were put to longer proof: Tobias Leopold drew a text which intimated that he should &amp;quot;tarry by the stuff:&amp;quot; and he submitted, expecting that his time would come, when his way should be made clear. Meanwhile, David Nitschman (who had first fallen in company with Anthony at Copenhagen) was invited, and con&amp;shy;sented to be Leonard Dober&amp;#39;s fellow-traveller to the West Indies, with the view, after seeing him settled at his post there, to return to his family at Herrnhut. </p>
				<p>Little preparation was needed for the journey: their brethren and sisters could furnish them with no outfit but their best counsel and their fer&amp;shy;vent prayers. Those prayers, however, &amp;quot;availed much,&amp;quot; for they were the prayers of faith, and that counsel was the wisest, which man, instructed by God, could give in such a case. It was literally this:--&amp;quot;In all things remember to follow the guidance of the Spirit of Christ.&amp;quot;</p>
				<p>Accordingly, on the 21st of August, 1732, like their Redeemer at the beginning of His ministry, &amp;quot;in the morning, rising up a great while before it was day,&amp;quot; they &amp;quot;went out and departed into a solitary place, and there prayed.&amp;quot; (Mark i. 35.) At three o&amp;#39;clock, &amp;quot;when it was yet dark,&amp;quot; (John xx. 1.)--the hour about which Mary Magdalene came to the sepulchre and found that her Lord was already risen,&amp;shy;--these first messengers of his resurrection to the negro-slaves in the West began their pilgrimage on foot, each with his staff and his scrip, accom&amp;shy;panied by Count Zinzendorff through the forest. At the place for parting, having commended them to God and the word of his grace, he said, &amp;quot;Bre&amp;shy;thren, what money have you for charges by the way?&amp;quot; They produced three dollars, and the count (whose whole income was expended in the cause of religion, and therefore always kept low,) added two ducats, making their whole stock about thirty-one shillings and sixpence. And this was the first missionary fund for preaching the gospel to the heathen, upon that plan which has since been adopted by almost all denominations of evangelical Christians! </p>
				<p>With these small means, they proceeded on their journey to Copenhagen, six hundred miles; hoping, when they arrived there, to be allowed to work their passage across the Atlantic on board some West Indian merchantman. On the road, having letters of recommendation, they called upon several pious friends, who hospitably enter&amp;shy;tained them, and bade them &amp;quot;God&amp;#39;s speed&amp;quot; when they departed, but who gave them no encourage&amp;shy;ment to hope that they should succeed in their design of carrying the gospel to the slaves. In fact, they rather disheartened the poor missionaries, by starting doubts and difficulties, to which they themselves gave no heed, except in so far as they saw that others were affected by the con&amp;shy;sideration of them. </p>
				<p>One devout lady, the countess de Stolberg, at Werngerode, alone appeared to view their project with favour. Having anxiously inquired into all particulars concerning their object and their prospect of obtaining it, she looked with compas&amp;shy;sion on the young man, Leonard Dober, and tenderly asked him a mother&amp;#39;s question,--&amp;quot;How could you bear to leave your aged parents be&amp;shy;hind?&amp;quot; He soon satisfied her, that it was from no lack of love to them, that he was going at his peril among strangers and savages, and that they would not want what little he might have been able to spare for them had he remained at home. She then, according to a practice frequent at that time among religious persons, requested him to draw a text of Scripture, on the occasion. He opened to these words, &amp;quot;Hearken, O daughter! and consider, and incline thine ear; forget also thine own people, and thy father&amp;#39;s house.&amp;quot; (Ps. xlv. 10.) The countess was deeply affected, and instantly said, &amp;quot;Go your way, and should they even put you to death, the Lord Jesus is worthy that his servants should be ready to lay down their lives for Him.&amp;quot; </p>
				<p>&amp;quot;These words,&amp;quot; said Leonard Dober, writing to the same lady, several years afterwards, &amp;quot;were a balsam to my heart, which before had been almost broken by the discouragements which others had thrown in my way. Your Excellency and Count Zinzendorff were the only persons who spoke comfortably to me!&amp;quot; What a preparation of mind for suffering, self-denial, and self-sacrifice was here! and how little besides these was ex&amp;shy;pected, when it was counted all joy to be told that, if their enemies killed them, their Master was worthy that they should die for Him! Their spirits indeed had been wounded,--wounded in the house of their friends; the scorn of the world they could well endure, but the want of faith among the people of God was hard to bear, by those who were themselves so strong in it, on the subject of their mission to the Gentiles. </p>
				<p>On their arrival at Copenhagen, they had to encounter fresh trials. Their scheme was re&amp;shy;garded by all with astonishment; and while some mocked and others pitied them, they were con&amp;shy;tent to be &amp;quot;accounted fools for Christ.&amp;quot; Their idea of labouring in the plantations as slaves, especially, was condemned as the height of infa&amp;shy;tuation. But they patiently persevered in apply&amp;shy;ing for license to go to St. Thomas, and to obtain a passage by some vessel bound thither. The latter was absolutely refused to them, on board of any of the Danish West India Company&amp;#39;s ships. Meanwhile, the report of their errand to Copen&amp;shy;hagen having reached the ears of the royal family, through Counsellor Pless, who from their arrival had kindly treated them, though he (like others) found it difficult to comprehend what spirit they were of, or how they could hope to accomplish the aim of their undertaking, the queen and the Princess Amelia condescended to desire an inter&amp;shy;view with them. To these august personages, the two humble disciples of a crucified Saviour told their simple story with such effect, that they were dismissed with the most gracious assurances of the royal good-will and future protection. The princess afterwards sent them a sum of money towards their expenses, and a large Dutch Bible. The latter gift proved peculiarly seasonable, and the apparently adverse circumstance of their being refused admittance on board of any Danish vessel, and being compelled to take their passage in a Dutch one, was not less beneficial in the result. The negroes in St. Thomas (the island having been formerly a colony of Holland) spoke a barbarous broken Dutch dialect,--the mission&amp;shy;aries spoke German; of course, without some preparation on the part of the latter, they would not have been able to make themselves under&amp;shy;stood by the slaves on their landing: but, though the crew of the vessel at first dealt roughly with them, Dober and Nitschman soon so conciliated the rudest, by that measure of &amp;quot;the meekness and gentleness of Christ&amp;quot; which they manifested, that, during the voyage of more than two months, the sailors delighted to help them in every way they could, especially in turning their German phrases into Dutch. They sailed from Copen&amp;shy;hagen the 8th of October, and reached St. Thomas on the 13th of December following. Previous to their departure, the Lord had given them such favour in the eyes of several persons, high in office at the Danish court, that, besides furnishing them with the means of paying for their passage, and procuring tools requisite for carrying on their respective handicrafts, they dismissed them with these words, &amp;quot;Go, in the name of God. Our Saviour chose fishermen for preachers of the gospel; He himself was a carpenter, and called the Carpenter&amp;#39;s Son!&amp;quot; </p>
				<p>It is recorded, that on the first appearance of the shore of St. Thomas, on which their hearts had been so long fixed, and to which their thoughts had been travelling every day with intensity of desire,--they were seized with pe&amp;shy;culiarly depressing emotions. This was not the failure of faith, but the fulness of joy, overflow&amp;shy;ing and presenting the symptoms of grief,--for the extremes of gladness and sorrow meet in this kind of feeling which they produce, and are expressed in the same language of tears, which, in return, yield relief to both. </p>
				<p>They landed on Saturday; and next day,--the third Sunday in Advent, on which the Gospel in the Lutheran Church (as it is in the Church of England) was, from Matt. xi. 2&amp;ndash;15,--John the Baptist&amp;#39;s message of inquiry to Christ, and our Saviour&amp;#39;s answer, &amp;quot;The poor have the gospel preached to them:&amp;quot;--they went in search of the &amp;quot;one lost sheep,&amp;quot; (Anthony&amp;#39;s sister,) whom they had come so many weary miles by sea and land to find in the wilderness, that they might bring her back to the good Shepherd who had laid down his life for her. After a little inquiry they reached the plantation on which she with her husband were located. Having delivered the salutation of her brother; at the desire of the parties, they opened and read a letter from him to his sister, in which, among the quotations from the New Testament, was the following: &amp;quot;And this is life eternal, that they might know thee, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent.&amp;quot; (John xvii. 3.) The Brethren began, then, at that same Scripture, and preached Jesus and the resurrection to the blacks, who had gathered round them while they were in conversation with Anna and Abraham, as Anthony&amp;#39;s sister and her husband were called;--christian names being preposterously given to heathen slaves, to whom the name of Christ himself was never declared. To this little company, after having told in few words, as well as they could, what the Lord Jesus had done and suffered to redeem perishing sin&amp;shy;ners, they said,--&amp;quot;For you also our Saviour has procured this salvation, and we are come hither on purpose to bring you the glad tidings!&amp;quot; </p>
				<p>Notwithstanding the German-Dutch in which they spoke, the poor negroes understood the drift of their discourse, and clapped their hands at the conclusion, in token of their joy at the message. Hitherto they had thought that such good things were all reserved for the white people. And was there not joy in heaven also among the angels of God, when, for the first time, the &amp;quot;faithful say&amp;shy;ing, and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners,&amp;quot; was made known to these children of Ham, suffering under the curse upon their father, and who &amp;quot;straightway received the word with joy?&amp;quot; There was probably not a humbler spectacle on earth, in that hour, nor one from which the wise of this world would have turned away with more contempt, than two fugitives from the heart of Moravia, the strong hold of corrupt Christianity, preaching Christ crucified, in a broken dialect be&amp;shy;tween their native tongue and a strange one, to an audience of Africans, who themselves spoke a jargon yet more barbarous, and had to strain their rude faculties to comprehend either the meaning or the sentiments of the address to them:--yet it may be believed that there was not a scene then exhibiting throughout this fallen world, more beautiful in prospect from the throne of God than this, when the first sickle was put into the harvest, which, since then, through a hundred successive years, has been yielding fruits in abundance, and beyond all precedent in any other Gentile field, where labourers sent by the Lord have gone forth. On a certain occasion it is written:--&amp;quot;In that hour Jesus rejoiced in spirit, and said,--I thank thee, O Father! Lord of heaven and earth, that thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto babes; even so, Father; for so it seemed good in thy sight.&amp;quot; (Luke x. 21.) And can it be doubted, that in &amp;quot;the joy that was set before Him,&amp;quot; when &amp;quot;He endured the cross, despising the shame;&amp;quot; that part of &amp;quot;the travail of his soul&amp;quot; was now seen by Him, in this commencement of gospel-preaching among negro slaves in the West Indies?</p>
				<p>Here then &amp;nbsp;upon the ground on which he had set his affections, when he for&amp;shy;sook his father&amp;#39;s house, and all the comforts of christian society: but here, like Abraham in Canaan, (called like himself by God out of his own country,) he had &amp;quot;none inheritance; no, not so much as to set his foot on;&amp;quot; (Acts vii. 5.) and, like his Redeemer, whom he had thus far followed out of the camp, bearing his reproach, &amp;quot;he had not where to lay his head.&amp;quot; Though the spirits of himself and his companion had sunk on the first sight of the island whither they were sailing, they no sooner found themselves among the people to whom they went, and engaged in the work for which they came, than their hope in God revived, and in the multitude of their thoughts his com&amp;shy;forts delighted their souls. </p>
				<p>Now, just while they were deliberating how they might contrive to lodge and live as cheaply as possible in that neighbourhood, Mr. Lorenzin, a planter, sent a message to the strangers, inviting them to take up their abode in his house, and promising to furnish them with all necessaries and comforts till they could provide for themselves. Their hearts and eyes overflowed with gratitude to their heavenly Father, who, knowing that they had need of such things, was thus graciously pleased to remind them, that they should take no anxious thought for the morrow, while they were engaged in his business. They were the more deeply affected with this offer of hospitality from one on whom they had no claim, when they considered that they had come hither under the expectation of being obliged to sell themselves for bond-slaves, and toil with the negroes, in order to do them any good. Thankfully, therefore, they accepted the kindness of their new-found friend, but providentially they had not long occasion for it. </p>
				<p>David Nitschman, being a carpenter by trade, soon found abundance of good employment, by which he was enabled to maintain both himself and his brother; for Leonard Dober, who was a potter, could find no clay in the district which he could work into serviceable vessels of any kind; his skill, therefore, profited him nothing. Mean&amp;shy;while they availed themselves of every oppor&amp;shy;tunity to shew the negroes that they came among them to do them good; and, though they had much to encounter, of jealousy on the part of some of the whites, and of contempt and disregard on the part of many of the blacks, in patience they possessed their souls, and were exceedingly en&amp;shy;couraged, when, from time to time, they perceived that they laboured not in vain, nor spent their strength for nought. Anthony&amp;#39;s sister and her husband were early awakened by their testimony, and others gave evidence that the word of God was making its way in their hearts, by the change which was wrought by it in their walk and con&amp;shy;versation. </p>
				<p>But they had been little more than five months on the island, when an opportunity of returning to Europe occurring,--for intercourse between Denmark and those distant colonies was unfre&amp;shy;quent in those days,--David Nitschman, accord&amp;shy;ing to previous agreement, took advantage of it, though much pained to leave his friend alone. Leonard Dober, however, on no account, would detain his journey-companion from his family. After making a slender reserve for his voyage, Nitschman left the small surplus of his earnings with Dober, for his maintenance, till he should find some means of supporting himself. The latter had not long to wait for this; he served a gracious Master, who soon provided bountifully for him. </p>
				<p>The governor, Herr Gardelin, hearing that the solitary missionary was thus circumstanced, sent for him, and engaged him as a tutor of his little children, took him into his house, and placed him at his table. Leonard Dober accepted the situa&amp;shy;tion on the express terms, that he should be allowed, after his daily duties in the family, to visit the negroes wherever he could gain access, and teach, as he might have opportunity, the whole counsel of God. </p>
				<p>In the cool of the evening, then, was the voice of the Messenger of Salvation wont to be heard, like &amp;quot;the Lord God&amp;quot;&amp;#39;s of old, &amp;quot;walking in the garden of Eden.&amp;quot; Here indeed it was &amp;quot;the voice of one crying in the wilderness,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Prepare ye the way of the Lord; make straight in the desert a highway for our God.&amp;quot; And did the sinners who heard it after the toils of the day, where, under the primal curse, they were eating bread in the sweat of their brow, on a soil which to them brought forth little besides thorns a&amp;micro;d thistles,&amp;shy;--did <hi rend="italic">they</hi>, like guilty Adam and his consort, when they heard that voice, run to hide themselves in the bushes? No; they heard and hailed the joyful sound; they learned to know and love it too; and, weary and heavy-laden as they were with the yoke of bondage, and sinking under the burthen of unrewarded labour, they ran forth from their huts to welcome it; and when the minister of Him who was &amp;quot;meek and lowly in heart&amp;quot; came to offer them &amp;quot;rest for their souls,&amp;quot;--the only rest the slave could hope to know in this life; the pledge, however, of rest eternal in the presence of God,--they ran forth from their poor huts, exclaiming in heart, if not in words, &amp;quot;How beautiful on the mountains are the feet of Him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace!&amp;quot; </p>
				<p>But Dober being visited with the fever which usually attacks strangers in those tropical regions, and which suspended his evangelical labours for awhile, grew dissatisfied with himself, that all his time, strength, and energies, had not been de&amp;shy;voted to these. His tender conscience reproached him, when he compared the ease and luxury of the governor&amp;#39;s mansion, in which he &amp;quot;fared sumptuously every day,&amp;quot; with the condition of a field-negro, to which he had in anticipation deter&amp;shy;mined to stoop, that he might give every moment he could seize, where such moments were so few and so precious, to the ministry of the gospeL He sunk under the humiliation of these thoughts, and when he had recovered from that temporary sickness, respectfully but earnestly prayed for his dismissal from his Excellency&amp;#39;s service. This was reluctantly granted. </p>
				<p>He then hired a little lodging at a place called Tappus, and earned a scanty maintenance by acting as watchman on some neighbouring plan&amp;shy;tations, and performing other small offices, which enabled him to procure bread and water, and little more, to sustain life. Amidst deep poverty, he was quite happy, because he was free, and the word of God not bound. Great blessing con&amp;shy;tinued to accompany his humble, fervent, faithful preaching, and after-years shewed that much of the good seed which he had sown by all waters, and on every kind of ground, had taken root, sprung up in due season, and bore manifold fruit. A year and a quarter had elapsed since his companion, David Nitschman, had left him, and, in all that time, he had heard nothing from his brethren in Germany, though as often as ships from Europe had come, at long intervals, to the colony, he had anxiously inquired for letters. On the 24th of June, 1734, intelligence being brought that a vessel had just arrived, he despatched a negro to ask the usual almost hopeless question; but the latter not returning so early as he wished, and the night coming on, he went himself to the harbour, and being weary, sat down by a watch-fire, at the way-side, to wait for his messenger. While he was musing, three men, whom he had not perceived coming, stood before him. He looked up;--one of them was his friend and brother, Tobias Leopold, who, with seventeen other missionaries, including the wives of four of the party, were come from the congregation at Herrnhut, to be stationed, some in St. Thomas, and the rest in St. Croix, an adjacent island, recently planted by the Danes. Dober and Leopold wept over each other at meeting, like David and Jonathan at parting. They afterwards spent the whole night in conversation on the subjects most dear to their hearts,--the progress of the church of God to which they belonged at home, and the prospects of that church among the Gentiles in the slave-islands, which Leonard Dober had already begun to build upon the foundation of the pro&amp;shy;phets and apostles, Jesus Christ himself being the chief corner-stone. </p>
				<p>Here this narrative must break off. </p>
				<metamark>* * * * * * * </metamark>
				<p>During the first years of the mission in St. Thomas, great hindrances, and occasional per&amp;shy;secutions were raised by some of the planters, to prevent the preaching of the gospel to the slaves. For several months in 1739, the missionaries, under false accusations, on which they were brought to trial, were cruelly held in prison; nor were they liberated, till Count Zinzendorff, in the latter year, arriving in St. Thomas, applied to the governor in their behalf, and obtained their im&amp;shy;mediate enlargement. When the count returned to Europe, he was entrusted with two petitions,&amp;shy; the one from the negro-men to the king of Den&amp;shy;mark, the other from the negro-women to the queen. These very petitions, supported by a representation from the count, when he reached Copenhagen, had so happy an effect, that a royal ordonnance was passed, dated August 7, 1739, securing liberty and protection to the Brethren in preaching to the slaves in the Danish colonies. </p>
				<p>The documents are well worth preserving. The following are exact translations:-- </p>
				<p>&amp;quot;&lt;span style="small-caps"&gt;To His Majesty the King of Denmark.&lt;/span&gt;&amp;quot; </p>
				<p>Most gracious Lord King!</p>
				<p>&amp;quot;Now we hope that your Majesty will com&amp;shy;mand that we may continue to learn to know the Lord Jesus. We remain immovable, if it please God our Lord; though we are greatly oppressed by men, who beat us and cut us, when Herr Mar&amp;shy;tinus (&lt;em&gt;Massa Martin&lt;/em&gt;) teaches us. They burnt our books, and say, &amp;#39;Negroes must not be saved; a baptized negro is fuel for hell-fire.&amp;#39; </p>
				<p>&amp;quot;They have put the brethren, whom God hath sent to us, and who are the only survivors of twenty, for three months, into the fort, and now they intend to drive them out of the country. They all appeal to your Majesty, and say, you have forbidden that the negroes should be made acquainted with our Saviour, and would shortly send Massa Martin away. But we do not believe this; and we pray your Majesty to allow us to be instructed in the knowledge of the Lord, and to remain in connexion with the Brethren&amp;#39;s church, for we wish to go with them to our Saviour. </p>
				<p>&amp;quot;We will he obedient to our masters in all things; we only wish to send our souls to heaven to the Lord Jesus. &lt;em&gt;Formerly we have cheated our masters, stolen provisions, run away, and been idle. But now things are quite different, as our masters themselves know very well. Many a negro, for his wicked deeds, has resolutely suffered his hands and his feet to be cut off; we will cheer&amp;shy;fully put our necks under the axe for the Lord Jesus, if our masters, as they say, will kill us.&lt;/em&gt; </p>
				<p>&amp;quot;God the Lord bless our gracious king a thousand times! </p>
				<p>&amp;quot;Written in St. Thomas, the 15th day of Fe&amp;shy;bruary, in the name of more than six hundred and fifty scholars of Lord Jesus, who are taught by Massa Martin.&amp;quot; </p>
				<p>Signed by &lt;span style="small-caps"&gt;Peter&lt;/span&gt;, and three other Negro&amp;shy;-Assistants. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;---- &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;span style="small-caps"&gt;To Her Majesty the Queen of Denmark&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;span style="small-caps"&gt;Magdalene&lt;/span&gt;, one of the female Negro-Assistants&lt;/em&gt;.] &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;span style="small-caps"&gt;Great Queen&lt;/span&gt;! &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;quot;When I was in Papaa, in Africa, I served Massa Mahu; now, when I am come into the land of the white people, they will not suffer me to serve the Lord Jesus. The white people will not obey Him, and they may do as they please; but when the poor black brethren and sisters wish to serve the Lord Jesus, they are looked upon as maroons (run-away negroes). </p>
				<p>If it seemeth good to the queen, may your Majesty pray the Lord Jesus for us, and also pray the king, that he would permit Massa Martin to preach the word of the Lord, that we may learn to know the Lord, and that he may baptize us negroes. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;quot;The Lord preserve and bless you, together with your son and daughter, and the whole family; I shall not cease praying to the Lord for you. </p>
				<p>&amp;quot;Written in the name of more than two hun&amp;shy;dred negro-women, who love the Lord Jesus.&amp;quot; </p>
				<p>&lt;span style="small-caps"&gt;James Montgomery.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sheffield&lt;/em&gt;. </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>