<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from James Montgomery to Mary Anne Rawson (English MS 414/78)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Mary Anne Rawson's The Bow in the Cloud (1834): A Digital Scholarly Edition</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John Rylands Library, Rawson/Wilson Collection, English MS 414/78</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline><placeName>Sheffield</placeName>
               <date when="1833-06-29">Jun 29 1833</date>.
            </dateline>
         <salute>My dear friend</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>
            When I received your note I had pre-
            pared a rough sketch of the enclosed narrative from
            memorandums. Which had lain on my desk ever since
            my promise (sometime about last Easter, I believe)
            to furnish you with something in the course of a few
            weeks for your Negro-emancipation Volume. I
            will not pretend to explain why this was not duly done;
            latterly, however, it has been neglected because I thought
            you would abandon your project when the ministerial
            plan of abolishing Slavery was made known. -- All
            this week, except today, I have been much occupied
            in other unavoidable business -- not my own, and
            therefore I cannot charge myself with evading your
            commission either from idleness or ^for personal interest.
            Here it is, such as it is, my humble contribution to your
            Volume! The matter I am sure is excellent; and of
            the manner[?] you will be hard-hearted indeed if you
            think worse than I do; but my pen, my head my
            heart itself, is worn[?] out on this, and almost every
            other subject of intense interest which in times past
            has engaged all ^my powers and affections. No matter --
            I must not trouble you with my troubles; forgive me for
            ever ???. If the narrative now sent does not satisfy
            you as suitable for your publication, do not hesitate to reject it.
            </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>With kindest regards to all at Wincobank, I am truly your friend</salute>
         <signed>J. Montgomery</signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript><p>XXX This is so late that I have no means of sending you this packet
            except through the Post Office.
         Perhaps the following new reading will suit the two last lines of the verse which you quote.
         (or see the top of the page)</p>
         <p>"What did it there, but to betray his thought,
         -- The Man, that traffic'd in his fellow-man!"
         </p>
         <p>
            "What did it there but to betray the thought
            Of Him who traffic'd in his fellow-Man!
         </p></postscript>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
