<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from James Montgomery to Mary Anne Rawson (English MS 414/82)
            </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <metamark function="folio-mark">82</metamark>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
            Both your letter and its enclosure from
            Mrs Townley, were very welcome. The former indeed gave me a
            minute or two's trouble, by imposing a task, though as light as
            the least feather that fell from the wing of Noah's Dove while she
            was flying over the waters without a shore, or where she was plucking
            the leaf from the olive just emerging above them; -- yet, after
            murmuring a little between my lips (my heart all the while
            reproaching me) I cast about in my mind for a thought, and
            having caught one caged it till this morning -- being interrupted at
            the time, and finding no spirit in the interval to meddle with
            plumage so delicate that I was afraid to touch it, lest like a
            butterfly's it should all come off upon my fingers, and I should
            have the mortification to send you a soiled and mutilated
            specimen for your repository of things "most good, most fair," of
            the kind, -- as I hope all, except my contributions, will prove to be.
            I was almost tempted to congratulate myself on some measure
            of success, in this instance, when, turning to your letter, I am
            deservedly (no doubt) for my vanity, humbled to find that
            you are to have an engraved vignette for your title-page,
            which will probably exclude a motto[?] so long as that which I
            have endeavoured to furnish. This would not have been too
            long, though consisting of twelve lines, if printed in the small
            but exquisite and distinct type, frequently used for such
            occasions. The lines, however, are written, and I may as well
            send them, leaving you to do what you please with them. If
            unsuitable for the frontispiece, they may perhaps be put into a
            corner towards the latter end, -- if the Book is ever to have arrived!
            Surely it will appear before the 1st of August, in spite of printers
            and engravers, who are by practice most accomplished procrastinators.
            I have been interrupted, as usual, here, and shall reconsider the <pb/>
            the subject of a motto before I take up my pen again -- this day's post
            being lost; but that will be so much time gained for an idler like me.
            XXX Perhaps the following from Milton would be a motto sufficiently
            significant, in connection with the phrase of the second title, "the
            Negro's Memorial," which is itself a comment on the first figurative
            one, "The Bow in the Cloud."
            <lg><l>He, with uplifted lands, and eyes devout,</l>
            <l>Grateful to heaven, over his head beholds</l>
            <l>A dewy cloud, and in the cloud a bow,</l>
            <l>Conspicuous with three listed colours gay,</l>
            <l>Betokening peace from God, and covenant new.</l></lg>
            Paradise Lost, Book XI.
            You will find these lines, with further allusions to the rain-
            bow (but these I think are decidedly most appropriate for
            your purpose) at the close of the eleventh Book of Paradise
            Lost. My opinion of their peculiar appropriateness for your
            title-page, is founded upon the circumstance of their application
            being <hi rend="underlined">general</hi> "betokening peace, and covenant new," whereas in
            the context, though each of the allusions is exceedingly beautiful
            yet <hi rend="underlined">immediate</hi> reference is made to the deluge, and ^<add>the</add> promise that
            no second destruction of the earth by a flood should ever ensue.
            After reading this passage in Milton, I am almost ashamed of
            my own puny[?] lines, and my weakness in having confessed that
            I was somewhat pleased with them, when I had first embodied the
            thought in readable verse. Do ^<add>what</add> you <del>please</del> <add>will</add> with them;
            and in everything that concerns this darling volume of
            yours, freely command any service which you think I can render.
            With sincere regards to Mr &amp; Mrs Read and the rest of
            my Wincobank acquaintances
         </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am, very truly
               your friend &amp; Servt</salute> <signed>J Montgomery</signed>
               <dateline>Sheff<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> March 22,
               1834</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <pb/>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Rainbow
               For the first of August 1834.</head>
            <lg>
            <l>Sign of the passing storm,</l>
            <l>Symbol of wrath gone by,</l>
            <l>Born of the cloud and sun, -- what form</l>
            <l>Of Beauty tracks the sky?</l>
            <l>From Afric to the isles of slaves,</l>
            <l>The Rainbow spans the Atlantic waves.</l>
            <metamark function="stanza-break">*   *</metamark>
            <l>Black, white, and bond and free,</l>
            <l>Castes and proscriptions cease;</l>
            <l>The Negro wakes to liberty,</l>
            <l>The Negro sleeps in peace;</l>
            <l>Read the great charter on his brow,</l>
               <l>"I <hi rend="triple-underlined">am</hi> <hi rend="underlined">a Man</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">a Brother</hi>, <hi rend="triple-underlined">now</hi>."</l>
            <signed>J. Montgomery.</signed>
         </lg>
            <postscript><ab>I have put a head to these stanzas, on the supposition
               that you will not use them as a motto. If you do,
               of course, the head all be unnecessary.</ab></postscript>
         </div>
         <pb/>
         <div type="envelope"><ab>Mrs
            M Rawson <lb/>
            at Josh Read, Esq.<lb/>
            Wincobank Hall<lb/></ab>
            <ab type="postmark">SHEFFIELD MA24 1834</ab></div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
