<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Eliza Conder to Mary Anne Rawson (English MS 414/16)
            </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Mary Anne Rawson's The Bow in the Cloud (1834): A Digital Scholarly Edition</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John Rylands Library, Rawson/Wilson Collection, Eng MS 414/16</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               Having, contrary to my intention, omitted sending an immediate acknowledgment of your polite and kind note, I must beg you to accept with my best thanks for its friendly contents, my apologies for having thus delayed them. It would afford me much pleasure to enjoy a few hours of your society, and I am not without hope of accomplishing this purpose at some interval before my return.
            </p>
            <p>
               A copy of your elegant volume was sent into my hands by Mr. Conder the evening before I left home. In the prospect of parting from my family, I had not much leisure of mind to consider its merits. Therefore, contented myself with ascertaining satisfactorily the two points on which, I believe, all writers—whether drinking at the fountain head of <name type="place">Castaly</name>, or sipping at its remotest confluence with the waters of oblivion—will be found most sensitive:—What mistakes have the printers made? and who are our companions? Both questions were unexceptionably answered both for Mr. Conder's verses and my own. Then, I felt obliged to close the book, and can guess at its further character only as it may be more or less favourably received in the review. The Critic seems to have possessed the good taste and tact to transmute the <hi rend="italic">one</hi> disadvantage—its late appearance—into a recommendation.
            </p>
            <p>
               I cannot suppress a degree of agitation in looking on the thickening shadows of this evening, and thinking of tomorrow dawn—feelings in which you have feared that you most deeply participate. A day so full of thrilling interest may not again wake until the last sunrise shall appear. I must offer my sincere thanks for your very kind enquiries, and am thankful to be able to say all is well. My Sister unites with me affectionate respects to Mrs. Reid, and best regards to your whole family. She begs also her kindest remembrance to yourself. Believe me,
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My dear Mrs Rawson,</salute>
               <signed>Yours with affection and esteem,</signed>
               <signed>Eliza Conder</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date when="1834-07-31">July 31st</date>
                  <placeName>West Dan House</placeName>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
