<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Thomas Clarkson to Mary Anne Rawson</title>
            <author>Thomas Clarkson</author>
            <editor>Christopher M. Ohge</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This is a born-digital diplomatic transcription of an unpublished letter.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Written on one side of a sheet of wove paper.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address><addrLine><placeName>Playford Hall</placeName></addrLine></address>
               <date when="1833-04-15">April 15 1833</date>
               <salute>Madam</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               Your letter appears to have been written a month ago,      
               <lb/>but for some cause or other it did not reach me till <del>beg[?]</del> a              
               <lb/>long time after its date, &amp; at the time I received it &amp; indeed                    
               <lb/>up to the present moment my thoughts have been deeply engaged
               <lb/>upon what I may call our common subject. This is one reason
               <lb/>why I did not notice your letter sooner; and another is that
               <lb/>having unhappily Cataracts on both my eyes I have not been
               <lb/>able to see either to read or to write for some time, and this
               <lb/>circumstance makes me aoord correspondence as mach as possible
               <lb/>With respect to the publication of your volume of Poems, no person
               <lb/>wishes it more success than I do, because no person can feel
               <lb/>himself more interested in the cause, which it is intended to
               <lb/>promote; indeed, I think that a work of this description may
               <lb/>secure the attention of some, whom prose-compositions would not
               <lb/>so much lay hold of &amp; thus a greater number of persons may
               <lb/>become acquainted with the case of the unhappy people whose
               <lb/>rights we advocate. I am sorry that I am so situated as
               <lb/>not to be able to contribute some little morceau towards
               <lb/>your Book. But these little things are so foreign to my
               <lb/>habits of composition, that I know I should not be able to
               <lb/>satisfy myself &amp; therefore must by you to excuse me.
            </p>
            <p>I am obliged to you for your wish that I may live[?]
               <lb/>to record the total abolition of Slavery. This would be most
               <lb/>delighlfull, but I have no expectation of it. I may, however
               <lb/>probably live to see the monster Slavery receive its death
               <lb/>wound from the British Parliament. This will satisfy me
               <lb/>and I shall be most truly &amp; reverently thankful for it--
            </p>
            <closer><salute>I am Madam yours very truly
               
            </salute>
               <signed>Thomas Clarkson</signed></closer>
            <postscript><p></p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>