<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from John Holland to Mary Anne Rawson (English MS 414/88)
            </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <metamark function="folio-mark">88</metamark>
         <opener>
            <dateline><hi rend="underlined">Sheffield Oct. 8th 1833</hi></dateline>
            <salute><hi rend="underlined">Madam</hi>,</salute></opener>
         <p>
            I am exceedingly concerned to have suffered[?]
            so many days to elapse between the reception of your kind
            letter by me and this reply, my apology must be the confession
            of a hope only extinguished by the lines on the other page, that
            I might have been able to have composed, at least a Sonnet
            in commemoration of the more auspicious circumstances in which
            the recent legislative enactment has placed the question of Slavery.
            If you still think worth your favour, the little communication
            which I have the pleasure of rendering so long ago, I thought that
            it might not be unbecoming on my part, to enable you to append
            to it, or place in its company some memento that the writer was not
            insensible to the fact of the virtual, though in reality still prospective
            abolition of Slavery under British authority. How imperfectly I
            have succeeded in this aim, the lines on the first page will, I am
            afraid afford but too clear evidence: whether or not therefore, they
            may be thought worth your acceptance, on the group above mentioned,
            must depend upon the view you take of the reason given, as compared
            with the demerit of the lines themselves. One happy feature in the
            theory of slavery, as now espoused is that however many old captives,
            and many who are neither old nor ailling, will die without seeing the
            day of actual emancipation, they will have the satisfaction of leaving
            that to their children which themselves never possessed -- the heritage
            of freedom -- and surely, it is not a light thing for us to say, that the
            registers of the West Indies shall no more record the birth of a slave.
            </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I remain, Madam,
            yours, very truly &amp; respectfully</salute>
            <signed>Jno. Holland</signed>
         </closer> <!--  -->
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
