<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from James Montgomery to Mary Anne Rawson (English MS 414/82)
            </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>82
            My dear friend
            Both your letter and its enclosure from
            Mrs Townley, were very welcome. The former indeed gave me a
            minute or two's trouble, by imposing a task, though as light as
            the least feather that fell from the wing of Noah's Dove while she
            was flying over the waters without a shore, or where she was plucking
            the leaf from the olive just emerging above them; -- yet, after
            murmuring a little between my lips (my heart all the while
            reproaching me) I cast about in my mind for a thought, and
            having caught one caged it till this morning -- being interrupted at
            the time, and finding no spirit in the interval to meddle with
            plumage so delicate that I was afraid to touch it, lest like a
            butterfly's it should all come off upon my fingers, and I should
            have the mortification to send you a soiled and mutilated
            specimen for your repository of things "most good, most fair," of
            the kind, -- as I hope all, except my contributions, will prove to be.
            I was almost tempted to congratulate myself on some measure
            of success, in this instance, when, turning to your letter, I am
            deservedly (no doubt) for my vanity, humbled to find that
            you are to have an engraved vignette for your title-page,
            which will probably exclude a motto[?] so long as that which I
            have endeavoured to furnish. This would not have been too
            long, though consisting of twelve lines, if printed in the small
            but exquisite and distinct type, frequently used for such
            occasions. The lines, however, are written, and I may as well
            send them, leaving you to do what you please with them. If
            unsuitable for the frontispiece, they may perhaps be put into a
            corner towards the latter end, -- if the Book is ever to have arrived!
            Surely it will appear before the 1st of August, in spite of printers
            and engravers, who are by practice most accomplished procrastinators.
            I have been interrupted, as usual, here, and shall reconsider the</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
