<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks on the Christian duty of putting an
               and to slavery</title>
            <author>Joseph John Gurney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Born-digital edition of The Bow in the Cloud</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>John Rylands Library</repository>
                  <idno>English MS 414-55</idno>
                  <!-- Published in The Bow in the Cloud; or, The Negro's Memorial. A Collection of Original Contributions in Prose and Verse, Illustrative of the Evils of Slavery, and Commemorative of its Abolitionin the British Colonies . London: Jackson &amp; Walford, 1834, pp. 89-95 -->
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>Remarks on the Christian duty of putting an
            and to slavery by Joseph John Gurney
            Sanganton that for
            That it is our bounden duty as Christians to
            labour in the cause of the abolition of slavery, is a proposition
            so reasonable &amp; obvious, that one might have supposed, no one
            could have doubted its it. Yet such is the perversion of heart
            &amp; intellect to which were all be mankind are liable, that
            sane persons have contrived to persuade thamselves, that
            their Christion duty, in reference to this subject, lies
            absolute inaction.
            In the first place, they urge as a plea
            for their non-interference, the curse promounced by Noah
            on Canaan "Cursed be Canaan", said the offended Patriarch?
            a servant of servants shall he be to his brethren? Gen. IX. 20
            Since the person by whom Noah had been offended
            was not Canaan, but his father Ham, its it is taken for
            granted by these objectors that "Canaan", is here put for "Ham".
            And since Ham, through his eldest son Mizraim, was the
            Progenitor of the Africans, it is concluded they conclude by them, first
            That the prophecy is accomplished in the slavery of the Negroes,
            &amp; secondly, that therefore in laboring for the emancipation of
            the Negroes, we labor against the declared decree of the
            Lord of all the earth.
            Now supposing this interpretation application of the
            prophecy to be correct the African race to be the true one,
            what can be more absurd than such a practical inference?
            The duration of Canaan’s servitude, is a subject on which
            does it contain
            the prophecy says nothing; much less is there the slightest
            intimation, that their cruel bondage was to have no end.
            Who then shall say, that the time is not come for its the
            of African slavery
            extermination. O who can deem it unreasonable to suppose
            that in effecting this object, God may be pleased to
            make use of human instrumentality.
            But I can by no means assent to such an
            interpretation of the prophetic record; &amp; which I believe
            received its accomplished accomplishment when the Canaanites
            who were left in the land of Palestine, became hewers of wood
            &amp; drawers of water -- to the degraded performers of
            the most laborious offices -- to their Israelitish Conquerers[?],
            who were [?] descended from Shem. It is highly
            probable ^also, that many of these enslaved persons[?] ^Canaanites
            were also exported from Tyre &amp; Sidon, &amp; became
            slaves to the European nations, the descendants of
            Japheth. And he said, Blessed be the Lord God of
            Shem, &amp; Cannan shall be his servant. God shall
            Canaan shall be
            enlarge Japheth &amp; Canaan ...... &amp; Canaan
            his servant. v. 25. 26
            Thus utterly vain, is the first plea of our
            objectors; but here we come in contact with a
            lewd plea -- <del>"The Israelites"</del> <!-- unclear words -->
The Israelites held their fellow men in slavery
a practice in which they acted under the authority
of their inspired Legislator." It is certainly true
that the ancient people of God were permitted by
their law, to make slaves both of the Canaanites
who were left in the land, &amp; of their captives taken
in war, &amp; equally so, that the bondage thus imposed
contrived during life. "Both thy bondmen &amp; bondmaid
which then shalt have, shall be of the heather that are round
about you, which they begat in your land, &amp; they shall
be you possession. And ye shall take them as an
inheritance for your children after you, to inherit them for
Levit XXV 44. 45.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
