<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Frederick Douglass to Helen Doncaster</title>
            <author>Frederick Douglass</author>
            <editor>Christopher M. Ohge</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This is a born-digital diplomatic transcription of an unpublished letter.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Written on four sides of a folded sheet of wove paper. It is a copy of the original.
               JRL labeled this "741(29)".</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <note>(Copy)</note>
                  <addrLine>North Parade, Halifax [GB]</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1859-12-07">Dec. 7, 1859</date>
               <salute>My dear Friend,</salute></opener>
            <p>Having, for the moment, very much upon my hands, I cannot go fully into the question
               of the right of an enslaved people to gain their freedom by a resort to force. Now
               indeed is it necessary that I should&#2014;I can, however, at once, give you the
               assurance that my advocacy of the cause of the Slave in England has no reference
               whatever to any plan or purpose involving a resort to arms,<!-- pb --> for the
               liberation of my Brothers &amp; Sisters in <del>bondage</del> Slavery&#2014;my
               mission is wholly peaceful. On that point you may feel wholly at rest. On the subject
               of Harper's Ferry, I can be equally explicit&#2014;I neither took part in that
               transaction no<corr>r</corr> counselled the taking it&#2014;but opposed the measure as fraught only
               with disaster and ruin, to the main object of the enterprize, which was to run off
               Slaves into the Mountains, and into Canada where they could protect <!-- pb --> and
               defend themselves. I do hope that a difference of opinion on any one point will not
               defeat our co-operating against Slavery at other points where we agree; but of that
               you must judge. The liberties of England are bulwarked about by ten thousand cannons.
               The Slave is <del>the</del> a victim of a constant <hi rend="italic"
                  >insurrection</hi>, by which his blood is drawn out drop by drop! It may not be
               altogether impartial to lay down the rules of submission to <!-- pb --> him, too
               sternly&#2014;especially since he has submitted already two hundred years&#2014;First
               pure, then peaceable.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your friend,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Frederick Douglass</name>
               </signed>
               <address><name>Helen Doncaster.</name>
               <lb/><addName>Secy. Sheffield <choice><abbr>A. S. S.</abbr><expan>Anti-Slavery Society</expan></choice></addName></address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
